<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Ionahs sermon, and Ninivehs repentance A sermon preached at Pauls Crosse Jun. 20. 1602. and now thought fit to be published for our meditations in these times. By Ro. Wakeman Master of Arts and fellow of Balioll Colledge in Oxford.</title>
            <title>Jonahs sermon, and Ninivehs repentance.</title>
            <author>Wakeman, Robert, 1575 or 6-1629.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1606</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 122 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 57 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A14642</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 24948</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S104651</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99840384</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99840384</idno>
            <idno type="VID">4884</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A14642)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 4884)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 862:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Ionahs sermon, and Ninivehs repentance A sermon preached at Pauls Crosse Jun. 20. 1602. and now thought fit to be published for our meditations in these times. By Ro. Wakeman Master of Arts and fellow of Balioll Colledge in Oxford.</title>
                  <title>Jonahs sermon, and Ninivehs repentance.</title>
                  <author>Wakeman, Robert, 1575 or 6-1629.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <editionStmt>
                  <edition>The second impression.</edition>
               </editionStmt>
               <extent>[8], 102 p. ; 8vo.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Ioseph Barnes, and are to bee sold in Pauls Church-yard at the signe of the Crowne by Simon Waterson,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at Oxford :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1606.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Running title reads: A sermon preached at Pauls Crosse.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:4884:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:4884:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>IONAHS SERMON, AND <hi>Ninivehs repentance. A</hi> SERMON PREACHED AT Pauls Croſſe Jun. 20. 1602. and now thought fit to be publiſhed for our meditations in theſe times.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> RO. WAKEMAN <hi>Maſter of Arts. and fellow of Balioll Colledge in Oxford.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond Impreſſion.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 12.41.</bibl>
               <p>The men of Niniveh ſhall riſe in iudgment with this generation and condemne it.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Printed at Oxford by Ioſeph Barnes, and are to bee ſold in Pauls Church-yard at the ſigne of the Crowne by Simon Waterſon. 1606.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:4884:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:4884:2"/>
            <head>To the Chriſtian Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> am not ignorant (beloued in Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus) how fruitful this age of ours is in bringing forth, to the viewe of the world, many new bookes, in ſomuch that wiſe men doe accompt it a fault of theſe times, that ſo many ſimple pamphlets are ſuffered to bee committed to the preſſe. VVherin, if I be iuſtly blamed with the reſt, for publiſhing theſe my rude &amp; raw meditations: accept of my iuſt excuſe, which is not (as commonly others alleadge for themſelves) importunity of friendes, for then I had printed my ſermon, aſsoone as I had preached it: being ther vnto ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly deſiered by many that heard me, as well strangers, as of my familiar acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance. But vnderſtanding ſince, that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny copies, as they were taken by note, are ſcattered abroad in <hi>Londo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> &amp; elſe where wherof ſome haue come vnto my hands, and finding them to be very vnperfect: I am the more willing to publiſh the ſame, as <hi>I</hi> delivered it, not adding, or detra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting,
<pb facs="tcp:4884:3"/>any one worde in the whole. And wheras in the ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d generall part, I larg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly amplyfied the ſeverall circumſtauntes, whe I firſt penned the I do now only point at them, in this printed copte, partly to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voide tediouſnes, &amp; partly becauſe I was conſtrated ſo to do, when I preached this ſermon beeing then cut off by the vnſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonablenes of the weather, and ſhortneſse of the time. But how ſimple &amp; vnperfect ſoever it bee yet for the arguments ſuke, befitting theſe heave times (which vvas an other cauſe of my printing it) I am the rather bould, to offer it to the conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of every well-diſpoſed Chriſtian: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeching God, who giueth a happy ſucceſſe to alour labours, ſo to bleſſe it, that he who readeth the ſame, may ſo meditate on the partence and long-ſuffering of God, and of his iudgement and iuſtice: that by the one be may be allured vnto repentance, by the other deterred from ſin. That as the people of <hi>Niniveh,</hi> bearing the wordes of <hi>Ionas</hi> Sermon, did all turne from their e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill waies ſo the people of <hi>England,</hi> rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb facs="tcp:4884:3"/>an expoſition on <hi>Ionas</hi> ſermon may all become newe converts vnto the Lord. That as the Lorde in mercy dealte vvith them, in with-houlding his puniſhments ſo he may as mercifully deale with vs as this time, in removing his heavy plagues, and fearefull iudgments from vs, and from our Land. Thus recommending is to thy Chriſtian meditation, and my ſelfe, &amp; all my ſtudies to thy daily praiers, I bad thee hartely fare well in the Lord. From <hi>Palioll Colledg in Oxford October. 10. 1603.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thine in the Lord, ROBERT VVAKE-MAN.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="analysis">
            <pb facs="tcp:4884:4"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:4884:4"/>
            <head>Ionah. 3.4.5.</head>
            <head type="sub">The Analyſis of the Text.</head>
            <list>
               <label>In theſe two ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes I ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue 2. <hi>generall parts.</hi>
               </label>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. Ionas ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon to the Ninivites, whereof there are 2 principall parts. <hi>ver</hi> 4
<list>
                           <item>1 The patience &amp; long ſuffering of the Lorde, in that hee did not preſently de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy theſe Ninivites, but gaue them a good ſpace to repent: <hi>yet</hi> 40 <hi>daies.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>2 His iuſtice and iudgement denou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cing deſtruction againſt them, if in the time allotted they would not repent and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend. <hi>And Niniveh ſhall be destroied.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. The Nini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vits repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance at Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas ſermon deſcriped in 4. circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances <hi>ver.</hi> 5.
<list>
                           <item>1 By their faith which was not fruite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe. So <hi>the people of Niniveh beleeved God.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>2 By their faſting, which was not privat. <hi>And proclaimed a faſt.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>3 By their attire, which was not coſtlie. <hi>And put on ſackcloath.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>4 By their number, which were not few, <hi>From the greatest to the leaſt.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>There are ſome other obſervations by the way pointed at, which are not ſpecifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in this table.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:4884:5"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:4884:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A SERMON PREACHED <hi>at Pauls Croſse Iun.</hi> 20. <hi>An.</hi> 1602</head>
            <head type="sub">The Text.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>Ionah <hi>3.4, 5.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Yet <hi>40.</hi> daies and Niniveh ſhall be deſtroved. So the people of Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niveh beleeved God, and proclaimed a faſt, and put on ſack-cloath, from the greateſt of them even to the leaſt of them.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>He<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Ionas</hi> the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet of the Lorde (Right Honorable,<note place="margin">The occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion &amp; ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument of this Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecie.</note> Right worſhipful, &amp; wel-beloued in the beſt beloued Chriſt Ieſus) had a long time in vaine preached and prophecied in Jſraells hee had an expreſſe charge giuen him
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:4884:6"/>from the higheſt, to goe and cry againg <hi>Niniveh</hi> the theife city of the <hi>Aſsiria<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s:</hi> that provoking them the gentiles to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, he might the rath r leane the obſtinate Iſraelits inexcuſable. But ſuch was, either his wilful obſtinacy that he would not, or his fraile imbecility that he did not regard his Lordes deſigne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: thinking with him ſelfe that his labour ſhoulde take little effect among ſtrangers to God and himſelfe, ſeeing it had done ſo ſmall good on Jſraell his owne people. And therfore, in ſteed of going to <hi>Niniueh</hi> whither he was bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, he ſhippeth himſelfe for <hi>Tarſhiſh,</hi> &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitteth himſelfe vnto the ſea, thinking thereby to fly from the preſence of the Lord. But behold he that is the God as well of the ſea as of the dry ſand, ſendes out his heraulds after him, a great wind, &amp; a mighty tempeſt: who raiſed the ſea, and rowled the waues, and rocked the ſhip, and ſo rowſed vp ſleepy <hi>Ionas,</hi> that he finds no reſt in the ſhip, the ſhip no ſafty in the waues, the waues no quiet
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:4884:6"/>in the ſea the ſea no calme in it ſelfe, vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>till the marriners had throwne out <hi>Ionas</hi> to appeaſe it. And yet ſee the provide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of a good God to a diſobedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nt Prophet: though he is caſt out, yet the Lord doth not caſt him of: though the mariners by his owne appointment takes him vp, &amp; throws him into the ſea: yet a great fiſh by the Lordes appointment ſwallowes him vp, and caſtes him on the dry land. Beeing thus delivered out of the deepe by the mighty hand of God, he had the ſecond time the ſame charge laid vpon him,<hi rend="sup">b</hi> 
               <hi>Ariſe &amp; goe preach to Niniveh the great city.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ion. 32.</note> Which the Prophet had no ſooner hard, but behold his obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to the Lords call.<hi rend="sup">c</hi> 
               <hi>He aroſe,</hi> ſaith the text, <hi>and went to Niniveh, according to the word of the Lord.</hi> Yea to <hi>Niniveh as great and excellent city of</hi> 3. <hi>daies iour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney,</hi> as the Prophet cals it. Yea <hi>he cryed againſt it,</hi> and ſaid as before J read vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you. <hi>Yet forty daies &amp; Niniveh ſhall be deſtroyed. So the people of Niniveh be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeved God, &amp; proclaimed a faſt, and put
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:4884:7"/>on ſackcloth, from the greateſt of them vnto the leaſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In which two verſes, for my eaſier proceeding, and your better vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, may it pleaſe you to obſerue, and conſider with mee theſe tvvo general partes.</p>
            <list>
               <label>2.<note place="margin">The gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall diviſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. two parts</note> generall partes.</label>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. <hi>Ionas</hi> ſermon to the Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nivites in theſe wordes, <hi>Yet forty daies &amp; Niniveh ſhall be deſtroied.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. The Ninivites repenta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce in the next wordes, <hi>So the people of Niniveh beleeued God, and proclaimed a faſt, &amp;c.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>The 1. ſetteth downe a meſſage from the Lord to a great Citie. The 2. decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth the converſion of a great city vnto the Lord. In the 1. mercy &amp; iudgment are preached by one, and that is <hi>Ionas.</hi> Jn the 2. faith &amp; good works are practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by many, &amp; they are <hi>Ninivites.</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold in the one, the duty of all true Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, to declare vvith boldneſſe the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:4884:7"/>Lordes wil vnto his people. Behold in the other, the duty of al faithful people, to obey with alacritie the voice of the Lordes Prophets. The 1. general part containeth in it theſe.</p>
            <list>
               <label>2. par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular braun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches.</label>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. The parience and long ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering of the Lord, in that hee did not preſently deſtioy theſe <hi>Ninivites,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">The ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diviſion of the 1. into 2. mebers.</note> but gaue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a good ſpace to repent. <hi>Yet</hi> 40. <hi>daies.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. The iudgement and iuſtice of the Lord denou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cing deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction againſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, if in the time allotted they would not ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dt <hi>And Niniveh ſhall be destroied.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>So that I may wel compare this ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon of <hi>Ionahs</hi> to <hi>Davids</hi> ſong Pſal. 101.1. <hi>My ſong,</hi> ſaith David, <hi>ſhall bee of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and iudgement.</hi> For lo while he ſayeth <hi>Yet</hi> 40. <hi>daies,</hi> there is a ſong of mercie. <hi>And Niniueh ſhal be deſtroted,</hi> there is a ſong of iudgement. Or to that<note n="f" place="margin">Himera.</note> river in <hi>Sicily,</hi> that parteth it ſelfe into two channels the one yeelding freſh vvater the other ſalt: for behold while he ſaith.
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:4884:8"/>
               <hi>Yet</hi> 40. <hi>daies,</hi> there is a ſtreame of ſweet water iſſuing fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the fountaine of Gods exceeding favour. <hi>And Niniveh ſhall be deſtroyed,</hi> there is an Ocean of bitter water running from the ſpring of Gods heauie diſpleaſure. The 1. is a word of comfort to al diſpaiting ſoules, <hi>Yet</hi> 40. <hi>daies.</hi> The 2. is a rod of correction to al preſuming ſinners, <hi>and Niniveh ſhall be deſtroyed.</hi> The one declareth vnto vs that God is a God of compaſſion, if wee wil repent, <hi>Yet</hi> 40. <hi>daies.</hi> The other that he is a God of iuſtice and ſeveritie, if we ſtil provoke him, <hi>and Niniveh ſhall bee destroied. Yet</hi> 40. <hi>daies, &amp; Niniveh ſhal be deſtroied.</hi> The 2. general part decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth the effecte,<note place="margin">The ſubdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the 2. into 4. circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</note> vvhich this Sermon wrought in the <hi>Ninivits,</hi> or their repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, which is deſcribed by 4. circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances.</p>
            <list>
               <label>by 4. cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</label>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. By their faith which was not fruitleſſe. <hi>So the people of Niniveh beleeved God.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. By their faſting vvhich was not private, <hi>and proclai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:4884:8"/>a faſt.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>3. By their attire which was not coſtlie, <hi>and put on ſack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloath.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>4. By their number which were not few, <hi>from the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt vnto the leaſt.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>They beleeved God.</hi> There is faith the true cauſe of good works deſcribed. 2. <hi>They proclamed a faſt.</hi> There is a good worke the effecte of a liuelie faith deci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phered. 3. <hi>They put on ſackcloath.</hi> There is the garment of humility expreſſed. 4. <hi>From the greatest to the leaſt.</hi> There is a mutual co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>verſion of al declared. 1. <hi>They beleeved God.</hi> Behold their heatheniſh infidelity is turned into religious pietie. 2. <hi>They proclaimed a faſt.</hi> Behold their luxurious feaſting is changed into mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate faſting. 3. <hi>They put on ſackcloath.</hi> Behold their royal robes are caſt avvay for ſimple rags. 4. <hi>From the greateſt of them vnto the leaſt.</hi> Behold the conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the ſinnes of all hath wrought repentance in all. <hi>So the people of Nini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veh
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:4884:9"/>beleeved God and proclaimed a faſt, and put on ſackcloth, from the greateſt of them to the leaſt of them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus you ſee (moſt deare &amp; Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> brethren) the ſumme &amp; ſubſtance of that wherof at this time, by the aſſiſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of the Almighty, and your accuſtomed patience, I purpoſe to intreate eve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the tenour of <hi>Ionas</hi> ſermo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the <hi>Ninivits,</hi> and of the <hi>Ninivites</hi> repentance at <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas</hi> ſermon. God grant J may ſpeake of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with the ſame ſpirit as <hi>Ionas</hi> did, &amp; that all this great &amp; Honorable aſſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>blie may heare and receiue them with the like fruite as did theſe <hi>Ninivits.</hi> And ſo J come to the particular handling of the words themſelves. <hi>Yet</hi> 40. <hi>daies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Partis. </seg>1</label> As <hi>Noahs</hi> doue came from the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of the floud, with an oliue braunch in her mouth. <hi>Gen.</hi> 8.11. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obſer. </seg>1</label> Even ſo this he a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly doue (for ſo the name of <hi>Ionah</hi> in the Hebrew importeth, &amp; S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Ierome</hi> on the 1 of this prophecy &amp; elſe-where ſo interpreteth it) co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth vnto theſe <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nivets,</hi> from the waters of the ſea, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:4884:9"/>a little before hee had beene almoſt drowned with an oliue braunch in his mouth, preaching mercy and peace vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them if they would repent, and turne from their wicked wayes. A ſingular ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument of Gods exceeding loue &amp; fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour vnto this city <hi>Niniveh.</hi> For hee might preſently haue ſent his Angel fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> heaven to haue deſtroyed it, as hee did the hoſt of <hi>Senacharib.</hi> 2. <hi>Reg.</hi> 19.35. He might haue conſumed it with fire and brimſtone, as he did <hi>Sodome</hi> and <hi>Gomer. Gen.</hi> 19.24. He might haue ſpoiled it with the edge of the ſword, as he did <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>richo Ioſ.</hi> 6.21. Hee might haue laid it in the duſt in the twinkling of an eie, as he hath done many, and as he is able to doe al the cities in the world. But behold the Lord is a <hi>pittifull God</hi> Pſal. 86.15. He ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth a milder courſe with <hi>Niniveh.</hi> He ſendeth his Prophet to her, and giueth her a day, and a day yea even <hi>forty daies</hi> togither, before he will powre downe the violl of his wrath, before he will ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecute his iudgments on her. And as a
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:4884:10"/>noble and worthy Emperour laying his ſieg, and levying his army againſt ſome famous &amp; renowned city: beholding in it the goodly buildings, the ſtatly walls, the high aſcending towers, the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of people, the numberleſſe nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber of babes and ſucklings; of infants &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent perſons: from a noble and heroï<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal diſpoſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is moved with the bowels of compaſſion towards it &amp; therfore in regard hereof doth not preſently batter it downe &amp; overthrow it, but firſt ſends his herauld at armes to proclame a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for certaine daies, and to offer peace vnto the ſame: right ſo doth the Lord of heave<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; earth deale with <hi>Niniveh</hi> that famous and renowned citty. He ſaw the ſtatelines of her buildings, her thouſand &amp; fiue hundred towers,<note place="margin">Munſter, Coſmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graph. l. 5. cap. 61. Ion. 4. verſ. vlt.</note> her high &amp; ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious walls, her multitude of citizens, her ſixſcore thouſand infants and inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent perſons, her head of cattell almoſt innumerable: all which did make the bowels of compaſſion to yerne within him, &amp;, before he would overthrow, it
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:4884:10"/>to ſend his Prophet as an herauld at armes, to proclame a parly <hi>of forty daies</hi> and to offer her peace if ſhee would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue it. Famous is that of <hi>Scipio Africa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus, that al things in warres ought to be aſſayed, before the ſword be drawen.</hi> And as famous that of the good Emperour <hi>Theodoſius,</hi> who, vntil tenne daies were paſt after he had beſieged any citty, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver offered violence to the inhabitants: ſaying and proclaiming every day, <hi>that thoſe tenne daies he gaue them, to the end they ſhould profit themſelus by his cleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cy, before they ſhould make proofe of his pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er.</hi> But as far as light excelleth darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, truth error, heaven earth: ſo farre, in pitty, mercy, and compaſſion, doth the Creator of all excell the beſt of all his creatures. Never was there any ſo pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull, as he the God of pitty. Never any ſo merciful, as he the God of mercy. Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver any ſo compaſſionate, as he the God of al compaſſion. O how often doth he perſwade by promiſes, how often doth he allure hy rewards how often doth he
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:4884:11"/>intreate by favours how often doth he aſſay al faire meanes to convert a ſinful ſoule, before he drawe out his ſword of vengance againſt him? O when did hee ſpoile any country once, before he had ſpared it often? Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> did he overthrow any natio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in one day, which he had not moſt louingly wooed before many a day? When did yet any place feele the iudgme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of his fury, that had not long before taſted the ſweetneſſe of his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy? For this was the rule of Gods owne law, this was the decree of his heavenly will, <hi>that no citie ſhould be deſtroyed, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore peace were offered vnto the ſame.</hi> as we read Deut. 20.10. And in the Goſpel it was our Saviours co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to his diſciples, that into what houſe ſoever they did enter: they ſhould begin the <hi>exordiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> of their meſſage with a <hi>pax vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis</hi> ſaying <hi>peace be vnto this houſe</hi> Luk. 10.5, and it is wel worth our obſerving, that vertues and miracles were firſt wrought in <hi>Corazin,</hi> and <hi>Beth ſaida,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their <hi>woe</hi> was pronounced againſt
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:4884:11"/>them. Matth. 11.20. Yea the fig tree in the Goſpell, although <hi>the Lord when he came and ſought it, found no fruit thero<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> ſhall not be preſently cut downe, but ſhall hane <hi>a yeare,</hi> &amp; <hi>a yeare,</hi> &amp; <hi>a yeare,</hi> to that, &amp; ſhal be <hi>digged,</hi> &amp; <hi>dunged,</hi> before it be deſtroyed Luk. 13.7.8. This alſo did the Lord of mercy do in the time of olde. He ſent <hi>Noah</hi> to the men of the olde world <hi>a preacher of righteouſnes.</hi> 2. Pet. 2.5. We ſent <hi>Lot</hi> to thoſe wicked <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domites</hi> in the ſpirit of meekenes to <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech them not to do ſo wickedly.</hi> Gen. 19.7. He ſent <hi>Moſes</hi> &amp; <hi>Aaro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> to the <hi>Aegyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian</hi> Exod. 5.1. He ſent Prophets from time to time to the childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Jſrael. He ſent <hi>Iohn Baptiſt,</hi> and our bleſſed Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, &amp; the holy Apoſtles, beſides ſignes in the hoſt of heave<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; tokens in the ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, to the people of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> before they were deſtroied. And although that citty were growen to a full meaſure of iniquity, &amp; to the very height of al man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of impiety, ſo that both the ſervants &amp; ſonne of God were ſlaine by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:4884:12"/>Sabaoth of the Lord polluted, the ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuary of the Lord prophaned, the lawe of the Lorde deſpiſed, the teſtimony of the Lord neglected; yet ſee the infinite mercy &amp; patience of a louing Lord be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, for a warning, <hi>ful forty yeares</hi> were allotted vnto her, before God ſent vp <hi>Veſpaſian &amp; Titus</hi> to ſack-it. As <hi>Euſebi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> in the 3. lib. &amp; 8 cap. of his Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical hiſtory reporteth. Before which time, how did the Saviour of the world call on her to repent, how did he weepe for her, how did he wooe her as the brid grome his ſpouſe to turne vnto him, &amp; to forſake her evil waies, how did he ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt his loue &amp; affection towards her? <hi>O Ieruſalem Ieruſalem thou that killeſt the Prophets and stonest them that are ſent vnto thee, how often would I haue gathered thee togither, as the hengather<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth her chikens vnder her winges, &amp; thou wouldeſt not.</hi> Mat. 23.37. J will not trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble you with many teſtimonies, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples out of the word of God, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme the truth of this doctrine, being a
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:4884:12"/>point ſo manifeſt. Looke but into the 9. chap. of the booke of <hi>Nehemiah,</hi> and the moſt obſtinate ſhall be conſtrained, wil he nil he, to confeſſe, that God is a God of much patience, and long ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring. The whole chapter is ſpent in this argument, ſetting downe in order, the great benefits and bleſſings which the Lord in his mercy had beſtowed vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the children of Iſrael in times paſt, their vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankfulnes vnto the Lord for the ſame, and yet the exceeding patience &amp; mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of the Almighty extended towards them. For firſt, as we there may reade,<note place="margin">Vid Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hem 9. reade the whole chapter.</note> he conſidered their aflictions in <hi>Aegypt,</hi> and hard their crie by the red ſea, he ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the deepe, and drowned their enemies in the mighty waters. He ledde the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the day with the pillar of a cloud, and in the night with a pillar of fire to giue them light. He came downe vpon mount <hi>Sinai,</hi> &amp; ſpake vnto them from heaven, &amp; gaue them right iudgments, true lawes, &amp; good commaundements. He gaue them bread from heaven for
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:4884:13"/>their hunger, and water out of the rock for their thirſt; he fed them forty yeares in the wilderneſſe, they lacked nothing, their clothes waxed not olde, and their feete ſwelled not. He gaue them king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes and people, hee multiplied their children as the ſtarres of heauen, and brought them into a good land: where they poſſeſſed houſes ful of goods, and did eare, and were filled, &amp; became fat, and lived in pleaſure through the Lords goodnes. But behold this people, whom the Lord had thus extraordinarily bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed aboue al the nation in the world be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came rebellious, &amp; behaued themſelues prowdly, and hardned their neckes, ſo that they harkened not to his comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements, nor reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bred the marvelous workes which he had done for them: &amp; yet for al this the Lorde forſooke them not. They made them a molten calfe, &amp; ſaid, this is thy God, that brought thee out of the land of <hi>Aegypt,</hi> and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted great blaſphemies; &amp; yet for al this the Lord forſooke them not. They were diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedient
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:4884:13"/>and rebelled againſt him, and caſt his law behind their backes, &amp; ſlue his Prophets ſent to convert them: and yet for al this the Lord forſooke them not. They did evil before him, &amp; ſinned againſt his iudgments, and pulled away their ſhoulders, and were ſtiffnecked, &amp; would not heare and yet for al this the Lord forſooke the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not, &amp; yet for all this did he not conſume the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but forbare the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> many yeares togither. O what a God of pittie, O what a Lord of mercy is this! <hi>abundant in goodnes, gracious, &amp; full of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paſsion, of long ſuffering, ſlow to anger, and of great kindnes.</hi> Ioel. 2.13. <hi>Reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving mercy for thouſands, forgiuing ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, tranſgreſſion, and ſin</hi> Exod. 34.7. How truly might he ſay of this people, <hi>All the day long haue I ſtretched forth my hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to a rebellious people, to a diſobedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t gaine ſaying &amp; vnbeleening people!</hi> Rom 10.21. How truly might he ſay that <hi>they had a long time grieued him, &amp; yet he had waited that he might haue mercy on the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>!</hi> Eſ. 30.18. How truly might be profeſſe
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:4884:14"/>of himſelfe, <hi>I deſire not the death of a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, but that the vvicked turne from his way and liue. turne you, turne you fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> your evill waies, for why will yee die ô yee houſe of Iſraell?</hi> Ezech. 33.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. What ſhould I ſay more (beloved in Chriſt Jeſus) God is the ſame God vnto vs al, as he was vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them: &amp; there is not one to be found in this great Congregation, from the moſt auncient father to the youngeſt child, but in ſome meaſure hath had ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of theſe things. Every one hath felt in himſelf God to be a God of much mercy &amp; expectation. For whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell</hi> had offended he ſtayed not at all for him, but threw him downe to hel. Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Adam</hi> had tranſgreſſed he deferred not his puniſhment, but draue him ſtraight way out of Paradiſe. But if we examine our ſelues we ſhal finde that he waiteth for every one of vs indeede, and forbea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth vs ſome ten yeares, ſome twenty; ſome to 30. ſome to 40. ſome to olde age, ſome to dotage. Yea hee ſpareth vs al becauſe he is the <hi>lover of ſoules</hi> as the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:4884:14"/>Wiſema<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cals him. He is patie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t towards vs and <hi>would haue none to periſh but al of vs to come to repentance.</hi> 2. Pet. 3.9. <hi>Hee maketh as though hee ſaw not our ſinnes, becauſe we ſhould amend.</hi> VViſd. 11.20. <hi>He prolo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geth our daies, although we doe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil againſt him an hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dred times.</hi> Eccleſ. 8.12. Let vs then be ware (beloved in the Lord) that we abuſe not the patie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce and long ſuffering of ſo good a God, leſt after ſo many ſweet ſhewers of mercie, &amp; pleaſant calmes of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort, hee powre downe vpon vs the bitter ſtormes, and hote thunderbolts of his iudgement &amp; indignation. And as the Prophet telleth <hi>Niniveh</hi> in this place: <hi>Yet forty daies &amp; Niniveh ſhalbe destroied:</hi> So yet a little while, &amp; if we will not repent and turne vnto him, behold a final deſtruction and overthrow ſhal over take vs. And ſo fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> my firſt obſervatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the patience &amp; long ſuffering of God, in that he did not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently deſtroit <hi>Niniveh,</hi> but gaue it a good ſpace to repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, <hi>Yet</hi> 40. <hi>daies.</hi> I now come to the ſecond note of my firſt ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:4884:15"/>parte, which was the iuſtice and iudgment of the lord, denouncing de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> againſt it, if in the time allotted it did not amend, <hi>and Nintveh ſhall be deſtroyed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And Niniveh ſhalbe deſtroied.</hi> Our Prophet doth not come onely with a ſong of Gods mercy to <hi>Niniveh,</hi> but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo with a ſong of iudgment; intimating that if they will not imbrace the one, they ſhal vndoubtedly feele the other. For albeit, being a ſtra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger to that place, a man of another country &amp; kindred, &amp; <hi>Niniveh</hi> large and ſpatious, and full no doubt of many barbarous &amp; cruel peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, he might in ſome ſort (becauſe hee was fleſh and bloud) be diſcouraged to deale ſo roundly &amp; plainely with them, as to denounce ſo heavy a iudgment on the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, for feare leaſt they ſhould haue kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led him: yet behold the courage &amp; au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dacity of a faithful Prophet, He prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth the diſcharge of his duty before the ſafety of his life: and, hauing receiued this meſſage from the Lord, he is not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:4884:15"/>(although he were but one &amp; that a ſtranger) to pronounce it in the midſt of <hi>Niniveh,</hi> yea peradventure before the king and nobles of <hi>Niniveh</hi> (for ſo it is probable) although it declare no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe then <hi>Ninivehs</hi> over-throw &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction. Out of whoſe bold and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full courſe of proceeding, let mee, by your Honorable &amp; Chriſtian patience (moſt deare &amp; bleſſed brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) giue this one note to my brethren and fellow-la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borers in the miniſtry: that, when they are to deliver their meſſage from the Lord vnto his people, out of theſe and the like places, they be careful,<note n="*" place="margin">A note for Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, from Ionas his bouldnes.</note> by our Prophets example, to lift vp their voi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces like trumpets, bouldly to reproue ſinne &amp; ſinners, to tell the houſe of <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cob</hi> his iniquities, &amp; <hi>Iſraell</hi> his tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions. Let them not be terrified to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare Gods iudgme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts againſt the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt, let them <hi>not be a fraid of the faces of men, for the Lord is vvith them.</hi> Ier. 1.8. They muſt with <hi>Amos</hi> preach the death of <hi>Ieroboam</hi> and captiuity of <hi>Iſrael</hi> eve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:4884:16"/>at <hi>Bethel</hi> in the kings chappel and in the kings court although with <hi>Amos</hi> they be baniſhed for it. Amos 7.12. They muſt with <hi>Michaiah</hi> prophecy the truth to <hi>Ahab,</hi> although with him they be ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for it. 1. Reg. 22.8. They muſt vvith <hi>Zachary</hi> tell the people of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> that <hi>becauſe they haue for ſaken the Lord, the Lord alſo hath for ſaken them,</hi> although by the comma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dement of the king with <hi>Zachary</hi> they be ſtoned for it 2. Chron. 24.21. They muſt with <hi>Iohn Baptiſt</hi> tell <hi>Herode</hi> that <hi>it is not lavvfull for him to have his brother Philips wife,</hi> though with him they be beheaded for it. Mat. 14.10. They muſt with <hi>Nathan</hi> tel <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>vid thou art the man</hi> 2. Sam. 12.7. They muſt with <hi>Eliah</hi> tel <hi>Ahab, it is thou and thy fathers houſe that trouble Iſraell.</hi> 1. Reg. 18.18. They muſt with <hi>Iehu</hi> tel <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoſhaphat, that for his wickednes the wrath of the Lord is vpon him</hi> 2. Chron. 19.2. They muſt with the <hi>Prophet</hi> tel <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſiah</hi> the king of <hi>Iuda, that for his ſin God hath determined to destroye him.</hi> 2.
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:4884:16"/>Chron. 25.16. They muſt with <hi>Azariah</hi> the prieſt tel <hi>Vzziah</hi> the king, <hi>that for his tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſgreſſion he ſhall haue none honour of the Lord.</hi> 2. Chron. 26.18. They muſt with <hi>Nehemiah</hi> rebuke the <hi>Princes and Rulers of Iſrael,</hi> for laying ſuch heavy burthens vpon their brethren, Nehem. 5.7. Finally they muſt with <hi>Ionas</hi> in my text tel <hi>Niniveh,</hi> yea glorious &amp; good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Niniveh,</hi> yea ſtout and ſtately <hi>Nini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veh,</hi> yea proud and populous <hi>Niniveh,</hi> that for her ſinnes it <hi>ſhallbe quite defaced and overthrowen.</hi> Thus muſt the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of God be bould to reproue ſinne in the mightieſt ones in the world, &amp; with the ſpirit of courage and audacity beate downe whatſoever lifteth vp it ſelfea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God.</p>
            <p>Iſpeake not this (beloued in Chriſt Ieſus) to condemne al kind of milde and gentle perſuaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: and to vphold <hi>the botte and indiſcreete reproovers</hi> of our time,<note place="margin">Indiſcreete reproovers not allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</note> who are ſo fervent &amp; forward in denou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing iudgment againſt the leaſt offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, that with <hi>Iames</hi> and <hi>Iohn</hi> nothing
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:4884:17"/>wil conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t them, but only <hi>fire fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to conſume them</hi> Luk. 9.54. They are the of ſpring of curſed <hi>Cham,</hi> delighting in nothing ſo much, as to <hi>vncover the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kednes of their fathers.</hi> They are, as Saint <hi>Bernard</hi> ſpeaketh of ſuch in his 78. Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, <hi>no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> correpteres ſed corroſores,</hi> not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proovers but gnawers. Not vnlike the <hi>Cynicke</hi> Philoſopher, who for his impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent taunts againſt all, was commonly called of all <hi>Convitiorum canis,</hi> the dog of reproches. For as thoſe <hi>Indians</hi> hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded like dogs, in lieu of ſpeech, vſe to barke, as <hi>Pliny</hi> in his 7. lib. and 2. chap. writeth of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: ſo theſe, in ſteed of ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king to their brethren after the manner of men, vſe to <hi>barke</hi> at them, after the faſhio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of <hi>dogs.</hi> My ſpeech doth not apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logize or countenance any ſuch, either dogged and in diſcreete raylers, or rude intemperate reproovers.</p>
            <p>J rather aime at thoſe in another ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treame, who are ſo farre from being to forward in reproving of ſinne, that they dare not take in their mouths but that
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:4884:17"/>cold rehrehenſion of olde <hi>Ely</hi> vnto his ſonns, <hi>Do ſo no more my ſons, do no more ſo.</hi> 1. Sam. 2.24. But as deceiptfull Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadours, either for feare of puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, or for hope of gaine, they forbeare to deliver the Lords Embaſſage vnto his people: Soothing them in their ſins and flattering them in their ſollies, and furthering the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in their iniquities. Thoſe are our <hi>temporizing preachers, our time ſeruing Prophets, our tre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cher Chaplaines</hi> who, either to ſatisfy the luſt of their hu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>morous Lord, or to delight the itching eares of their vaine auditors, ſpeake no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but <hi>place<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tia,</hi> court phraſes, ſweet and pleaſing words: that ſow pillowes vnder mens elbowes, and build vp their ſinnes as a wall, and daub vp their filthy corruptions with the vntempered mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of palpable adulatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Whom I may iuſtly brand with the ſame name as <hi>Cra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes</hi> the <hi>Thebane</hi> did thoſe paraſites, of his time who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hee called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: becauſe, ſitting at great me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s tables, they were ready with that <hi>cunning diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bler</hi>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:4884:18"/>in the comody to ſay, <hi>Ais, aio? ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gas? nego.</hi> Whatſoever they affirmed they would affirme the ſame, and what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever they denyed they would bee as ready to deny though never ſo vntruly. right ſo, beloved, I am afraid our church hath to many ſuch <hi>fawning and flatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring</hi> Miniſters: who ſitting at noble me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s tables (if happely they be thervnto ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted) for feare of diſpleaſing, will ſay as they ſay: although their owne conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence I doubt not many times tels them they haue ſaid amiſſe. <hi>Speaking good of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill, and evil of good, putting darkeneſſe for light, and light for darkeneſſe, bitter for ſweet, and ſweet for ſower</hi> to vſe the words of the Prophet Eſa. 5.20. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Making marchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe of the vvord of God,</hi> as the Apoſtle ſpeaketh 2. Cor. 2. vlt. <hi>and ſelling the cauſe of the Lord for a meales meat,</hi> or as the Prophet tels vs <hi>for handfulls of bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and peeces of bread.</hi> Ezech. 13.19. J ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not more fitly reſemble ſuch falſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets to any, then to that flattering and
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:4884:18"/>diſſembling Prieſt of <hi>Iuppiter:</hi> who whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Alexander</hi> the great (as <hi>Plutarch</hi> in his life teſtifieth) came to the oracle, ſalu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted him by the name of <hi>Iuppiters ſonne,</hi> &amp; all to get ſome great preſent &amp; large-reward fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him: ſo they, to procure the ſooner vnto themſelues ſome promoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Eccleſiaſtical, wil make the <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi> of the world beleeue, that they are <hi>Demy Gods</hi> or at the leſtwiſe a degree a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue the natural conditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the ſonnes of men. They are fit chaplaines for ſuch radies as the mother of <hi>Cyrus</hi> was, who, as <hi>Plutarch</hi> reporteth, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>manded, that whoſoever ſpake to the king, he ſhould vſe <hi>ſoft &amp; ſilken words:</hi> for ſurely in their preaching and reaching before ſuch great ons of the world, they vſe noe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther but ſuch ſoft phraſes &amp; ſilken ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches as ſhal befit their humours. And as the natural biſtorian in his 2. lib. &amp; 41. ca. of his hiſtory reporteth of the hearb called <hi>Heliotropium,</hi> that it regardeth &amp; looketh towards the ſunne: ever as hee goeth turning with him at all howers.
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:4884:19"/>yea even alſo when he is ſhadowed vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a cloude: ſo doe they, in the whole courſe of their miniſtery, regard &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider their Lords and Ladies humours, and thervnto do they apply themſelves at all times, yea eve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> then alſo whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they are covered with the cloudes of many groſſe and crying ſinnes. So that I may truly ſay of ſuch, as the <hi>Philoſopher</hi> did of the like, who, as <hi>Nicephorus</hi> reporteth in the 10. lib. &amp; 42. cap. of his Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical hiſtorie, comming into an Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours court, &amp; there ſeeing many ſooth vp great men in their ſins, ſaid of them, <hi>purpura<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ipſos magis quam Deum colere,</hi> that they did more reverence purple robes then God himſelfe and J am per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded (beloved in Chriſt Jeſus) that they who thus ſooth vp the mighty po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentants of the world in their tranſgre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſions, <hi>quod purpuram ipſimagis quam de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um colant,</hi> that they more reſpecte the cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tenance of man, then the favour of the everliving God. For otherwiſe they would never, as many times they doe,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:4884:19"/>conceale the councel &amp; wil of God, to gaine a little commodity &amp; preferment at the hands of a mortal man. And if it happen, (beloued) that theſe men come abroad at any time, to preach amonge the vulgar ſorte in meaner places, they haue ſo vſed themſelves to a ſmooth &amp; pleaſing vaine, that even then J may ſay of them, as <hi>Diogenes</hi> the <hi>Cynicke</hi> ſaid of orators, as it is in the 9. lib. and 19. cap. <hi>Elian. de varia hiſtor.</hi> that they are <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> the very ſlaues &amp; vaſſals of the common people. For to win their leaſt favours, they wil be favourable to their greateſt ſins. And as <hi>Pliny</hi> in his 5. lib. &amp; 15. chap. ſaith that the river <hi>Iordan is a pleaſant river, winding &amp; turning in &amp; out, ſeeking as it were for loue &amp; favour, and applying it ſelfe to pleaſe the neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tries.</hi> So do theſe <hi>time-ſerving preachers</hi> turne &amp; winde themſelves in their ſermons to the multitude: ſeeking rather to win their favours by flatering them in their ſinnes, then to diſcharge their owne duties to God by revealing
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:4884:20"/>his wil vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. But let theſe men con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider howe much the Lorde is offended with ſuch deceitful ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dling of his word. Let them co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider the grievous co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plaint of the Lord againſt ſuch falſe Prophets, <hi>who healed the hurt of the daughter of his people with ſweete wordes, ſaying peace, where there was no peace.</hi> Jer. 6.13. Let them co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider how much he was moued with them that <hi>taught vanities, &amp; ſpake the viſion of their owne hearts, &amp; not out of the mouth of the Lord. Saying to every one that vvalked after the ſtubbornes of his owne hart, no evil ſhal come vpon you, prophecying falſe dreames &amp; cauſing the people of the Lord to erre by their lies and by their flatteries.</hi> Ier. 23. Finally let the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider the ſevere iudgme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the Lord pronou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ced againſt ſuch faithleſſe meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gers in the ſame Prophet. Behold they that flatter the people in their ſinnes, &amp; <hi>ſar that the ſword &amp; famine ſhal not bee in the land, by ſword &amp; famine ſhal theſe Prophets be conſumed.</hi> Jer. 14.15.</p>
            <p>Wherfore to conclude this point, let
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:4884:20"/>vs (beloved) I ſpeake this to al my bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren and fellow-labourers in this holie buſines, let vs I ſay, as truſtie Embaſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dours, boldly deliuer our Lordes Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſage: <hi>not fearing him that can kill the body only, but him that can caſt both body and ſoule into hell fire.</hi> Matt. 10.28. And yet let vs not ſeeke to gal &amp; greeue the wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded conſcience of our weake audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, by to raſh &amp; indiſcreete doubling &amp; redoubling <hi>woes</hi> vpon them, alvvaies killing the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vvith the killing letter of the <hi>law.</hi> Let vs take heede leaſt if we thus alwaies preach to others iudgme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out mercy, wee our ſelues bee iudged of the Lord without mercy. Let vs rather by our Prophets example, keeping the golden meane, temper them both togi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Let vs ſometimes with the ſweete balme of the Goſpel bind vp the broke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> harted: and yet ſometimes alſo with the hard ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mer of the law bruze and breake downe the ſtrength of impietie. Let vs ſometimes as good chirurgions applie pleaſant lenitines to ſupple: &amp; yet ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:4884:21"/>alſo ſharpe coraſines to exaſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate the feſtered wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds of our ſicke pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tients. Let vs ſomtimes like skilful Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions miniſter comfortable refections to cheriſh; &amp; yet ſomtimes alſo ſharpe and bitter potions to offend their diſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pered ſtomacks. Let vs ſomtimes with that good <hi>Samaritane</hi> Luk. 10, with the oile of mercy cheere vp the fainting co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſcience of a poenitent Chriſtian: &amp; yet ſometimes alſo with the wine of repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion rub vp the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tagious maladies of hard harted worldlings. Let vs ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times with the ſons of <hi>Iacob</hi> ſtand vpon the mou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t <hi>Gerizzim</hi> to bleſſe, &amp; yet ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times alſo vpon the mou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t <hi>Eball</hi> to curſe the Lords enemies Deut. 27.13. Let vs ſometimes with S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Paul Come in the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of meekenes to comfort: and yet ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tims alſo with the ſame Apoſtle with the rod of correction to controule</hi> 1. Cor. 4. 21. Let vs ſometimes ſay with our mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>pax vobis, peace be vnto you</hi> Luk. 24.36. &amp; yet ſometimes alſo <hi>vae vobis, woe be vnto you.</hi> Matt. 23.13. Let vs ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:4884:21"/>be like <hi>that ſoft voice wherin God came</hi> 1. Reg. 19.12. and yet ſometimes alſo like <hi>Iohn Baptist the voices of criers or crying voices</hi> in the wildernes of this world Math. 3.3. Let vs ſometimes bee like <hi>Barnabas ſons of Conſolatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> Act. 4.36. and yet ſometimes alſo like <hi>Iames &amp; Iohn</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>the ſons of thunder</hi> Mark. 3.17. Laſtly let vs ſometimes come with <hi>Ionas</hi> in my text with a ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge of mercy as in the firſt part of his ſermo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>yet</hi> 40. <hi>daies:</hi> and yet ſometimes alſo with a ſonge of iudgment as it followeth in the ſecond <hi>and Niniveh ſhalbe deſtroied.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And Niniveh ſhalbe deſtroyed.</hi> And heerein a word before I proceede fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: Let me remoue a ſtumbling blocke of offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, which may ariſe to the weake out of theſe words: For wheras our Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet here ſetteth downe, that after the ſpace of 40. <hi>daies, Niniveh ſhoulde bee deſtroied,</hi> it is manifeſt in the laſt verſe of this 3. chapter that <hi>God repented of this evil which he had purpoſed to do vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it, &amp; he did it not.</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Quaeſtion </seg>
               </label> Howe then is the
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:4884:22"/>councel of the Lord infallible, howe is the verity of his word immutable, howe are his decrees vnreſiſtable, how is his iudgment here denou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ced by <hi>Ionas</hi> ine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitable? <hi>and Niniveh ſhalbe deſtroyed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Opinion </seg>1</label> For anſwere where vnto we muſt ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, that ſome of the auncient fathers in the primitiue church haue bin of this opinion, that by <hi>Niniveh</hi> here is vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, the ſin &amp; iniquity of the people of <hi>Niniveh.</hi> As if the Prophet had ſaid, <hi>Yet forty daies &amp; Niniveh ſhal be deſtroied,</hi> that is, not the me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the wals, &amp; the buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings of <hi>Niniveh,</hi> but the ſins &amp; tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of <hi>Niniveh;</hi> the ſinful city ſhal become an holy city, the idolatrous peo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple a ſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ctified people, the height of their impietie ſhalbe deſtroied by the teares of their penite<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cy. Thus ſhal ſinful <hi>Nini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veh</hi> be quite defaced, thus ſhall vngod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Niniveh</hi> be overthrowne. Of this o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Auſten</hi> in his 21, lib. &amp; 24. chapter <hi>de civitate dei.</hi> Where he ſaith thus. That <hi>God vſeth to ouerthrow ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners two manner of waies. Either when
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:4884:22"/>he puniſheth the men for ſins co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted, as he did the Sodomites</hi> Gen. 19.25. <hi>or when he deſtroyeth the ſins of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> through their vnfeined repenta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, as in theſe Ninivits.</hi> And in this ſence, ſaith S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Austen,</hi> is the word of the Lord true, that <hi>Niniveh</hi> in her people &amp; buildings ſtood ſtil, but in her wicked waies and tranſgreſſions <hi>ſhe was overthrowne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But ſaving the iudgme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of ſo learned a father (whom notwithſtanding of alo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the fathers generally for his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of the Scripture I hould to bee moſt worthy of reverence) I rather faſten vppon another interpretation of theſe wordes.<note place="margin">2. Opinion</note> And that is that they are ſpoken by our Prophet with a conditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> implied in them, as if hee had ſaide: the Lord your God is a patient God, he will not wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d you before he warne you. Loe he giveth you <hi>yet</hi> 40 <hi>daies</hi> more to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>think your ſelues, if in this ſpace you wil not turne vnto him, then aſſuredly <hi>you ſhalbe deſtroyed.</hi> And this I rather take to bee the Prophets meaning in this
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:4884:23"/>place: not onely for that the whole cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent of our latter &amp; ſounder interpreters doe agree here vnto, but alſo, becauſe I know this manner of denouncing iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, is verie vſual vvith the ſpirite of God in holy ſcripture. Witnes that one place inſteede of all, in the prophecie of <hi>Ieremy, I will ſpeake</hi> (ſaith the Lord) <hi>ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly againſt a natio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, againſt a kingdom, to plucke it vp and to roote it out, and to deſtroy it. But if this nation againſt who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I haue pronounced, turne from their wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kednes: I vvill repent of the plague that I thought to bring vpon them. Ier.</hi> 18.7.8. There you ſee, the condition is ſet down in expreſſe words. <hi>If they turne fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their wickednes I will repent.</hi> But elſewhere it is neceſſarily implyed and vnderſtood as for example. When <hi>Abimelech</hi> the king of <hi>Gerar,</hi> had tooke vnto him <hi>Sara,</hi> the wife of <hi>Abraha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>:</hi> God ſaid vnto him, <hi>thou art but a dead ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> becauſe of the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man which thou haſte taken. Geneſ.</hi> 20.3. Here the iudgement ſeemeth abſolute. But this condition muſt needes bee vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:4884:23"/>that he was but a dead man, if hee did not reſtore the woman without touching her bodie. For vvhen he had purged himſelfe <hi>with an vpright minde, and innocent hand haue I done this:</hi> the Lorde forbare to execute this ſentence on him. So likewiſe the Prophet <hi>Eſaie</hi> biddeth <hi>Ezechiah</hi> from the Lorde. <hi>to ſet his houſe in order, for hee ſhould die &amp; not liue, Eſ.</hi> 38.1. What ſpeech can be more abſolute the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this? And yet we muſt needs confeſſe, that this condition is therein contained: thou ſhalt die, if thou ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peaſe not the wrath of God by thy tears and vnfained repentance. For when he had once ſo done, the Lord removed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way this iudgement, <hi>and added vnto his daies fifteene yeares,</hi> as it is in the ſame chapt. Agreeable to this is that of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid,</hi> vvho when he had killed <hi>Vriah the Hittite,</hi> and taken his wife vnto himſelf: the Lord tolde him, that for this, <hi>the ſword ſhould neuer depart from his houſe</hi> 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 12.10. A ſentence without ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception: and yet when he confeſſed, that
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:4884:24"/>in this he had <hi>ſinned againſt the Lorde</hi> (a condition no doubt in the former iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment implyed) it was tould him by <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than,</hi> that <hi>the Lord had put away his ſin and he ſhould not die: verſ.</hi> 13. So in the words of my text, here is deſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced by <hi>Ionas</hi> againſt <hi>Niniveh, yet</hi> 40 <hi>daies and Niniveh ſhall be deſtroyed.</hi> And yet, <hi>Niniveh</hi> repenting, the Lord withholdeth his iudgements from it: &amp; therefore we muſt needes vnderſtand a condition in the words: <hi>yet</hi> 40. <hi>daies</hi> and if <hi>Niniveh</hi> go on ſtil in her vvickednes, doubtleſſe <hi>Niniveh</hi> for her wickedneſſe ſhal be deſtroyed. Having thus cleared this doubt, and made manifeſt the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of our Prophet: let vs now come to the next obſervatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning was propoſed out of theſe words <hi>and Niniveh ſhal be deſtroied.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obſervat. </seg>2</label> Jt is reported of <hi>Tamberlaine</hi> that mighty conqueror of his time, that whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he laid ſiege to any city: he diſplaied the firſt day his white flag before the ſame, as a toke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of his clemencie if they would
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:4884:24"/>yeeld vnto him: VVhich if they then re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed, the next day he ſet vp his red flag, as threatning the ſhedding of their bloud, if they remained obſtinat: wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at if they were not moved, the third day he advanced his blacke flag, to ſignifie, that the dore of all pittie &amp; compaſſion was now ſhut vp, and that nothing was to be expected, but vtter ruine and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation. The like courſe, in ſome pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion, doeth the Lorde of heaven and earth take with his citty <hi>Niniveh:</hi> he firſt diſplaieth his white flag of mercie, not for a day with <hi>Tamberlaine,</hi> but eve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for 40, <hi>daies</hi> togither: whereat if they wil not yeeld, they ſhall beholde the red flag of his ſeverity, nay the blacke flag of his irrevocable iudgement, denoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing their vtter overthrowe and deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. For the ſaying is moſt true, <hi>Laeſa patientia fit furor,</hi> the patience of the Lord too ſarre provoked, is turned into fury. <hi>Seravenit, ſed certa venit vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cta:</hi> it is long ere hee revenge himſelfe on ſinners, but hee paies the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with a wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:4884:25"/>at the laſt. And howſoever the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment of malefactors come ate, yet in never miſſeth in the end. As the<note n="*" place="margin">Plin. lib. 2. c. 7.</note> hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then man by the light of nature could tell vs. <hi>Lento graduad vindictam divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na procedit ira. Tarditatem<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> iudicij gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitate pe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſat</hi> ſaith<note n="*" place="margin">Valerius Maximns lib. 1.</note> another. God is ſaid to haue leaden ſeete becauſe hee com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth ſlowly to execute vengance; but hands of iron becauſe when he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth he ſtricketh home. And by how much the longer he expecteth our ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, ſo much the more ſtrictly hee will iudge vs if we do neglect. Experience teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth vs that the axe the higher it is lifted, the heavier it falleth. A ſtone the fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it is caſt vp into the aier falleth with greater force vpon the earth. Awa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter courſe the more it is ſtopped, when it breaketh forth, runneth with greater violence: even ſo the longer the Lorde heareth &amp; forbeareth to puniſh the ſins of men, the heavier wil his puniſhment be in the end. And howſoever hee can bee content along ſeaſon to haue pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:4884:25"/>with them: yet at the laſt, as hee ſpeaketh by the Prophet, <hi>he will over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne, overturne, overturne, Ezech.</hi> 21.27. Where, by thrice repeating of the word, is vnderſtood an abſolute deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and deſolation indeed. <hi>Pliny</hi> in his 8. lib. and 7. cap. and <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> in 9. lib. &amp; 46. cap. <hi>de natura animalium</hi> doe write of the <hi>elephant,</hi> that by nature he is very milde and gentle; and others ſay, that he ſuffereth many wro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gs of inferior beaſts but beeing ſtill provoked by them to wrath his fury is not pacified, vntil hee hath revenged himſelfe to the ful. That which is ſaid to be true of the creature, is in this ſenſe moſt true of the creator of al things God himſelfe. His very na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and eſſence is, to bee <hi>A God ful of compaſſion and mercy, flow to anger, and of great kindnes. Pſal.</hi> 103.8. Hee ſuſtei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth many wrongs of the ſons of men: being cruſhed with their ſins, <hi>as a cart is laden with ſheaues,</hi> to vſe the words of the Prophet: wherwith if they ſtil con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue to load him, he wil eaſe himſelfe of
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:4884:26"/>his burden, and caſt it on the ground of confuſion. And albeit, as the Pſalmiſt ſpeaketh, <hi>he be patient, and is prouoked e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very day: yet if a man will not turne, hee will whet his ſword, he will bend his bow, &amp; make it ready. Pſa.</hi> 7.12. For it is moſt true which <hi>Gregory</hi> ſaith in his 33. book of morals and 15. chapter. <hi>Vt pius, ita iuſtus eſt conditor.</hi> As our maker is mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciful, ſo is he likewiſe iuſt. <hi>Gracious and righteous is the Lord,</hi> Pſal. 25.8. <hi>gracious</hi> in the multitude of his mercies, &amp; <hi>righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous</hi> in the ſeveritie of his iudgements. <hi>Gracious</hi> to them that turne vnto him, <hi>righteous</hi> to them that caſt him fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. <hi>The Lord is ſlow to anger,</hi> there is his pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience to penitent ſinners: <hi>but he is great in power, &amp; wil not ſurely cleere the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked.</hi> Nahum. 1.3. there is his iudgement to impenitent reprobates. <hi>I haue a longe time holden my peace at your ſins, I haue beene ſtill, &amp; reſtrained my ſelfe,</hi> there is his long ſuffering declared: <hi>but now will I cry like a traveiling woman, I wil de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy &amp; devour at once.</hi> Eſ. 42.14. there
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:4884:26"/>is his heavy wrath deſcribed. <hi>The Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty is a patie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t rewarder,</hi> there is mer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cy offered to him that wil receiue it: <hi>but he will not leaue the wicked vnpuniſhed.</hi> Eccleſ. 5.4. there is iuſtice pronounced to him that wil neglect it.</p>
            <p>Thus you ſee (moſt deare and Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian brethren) that loue &amp; wrath, pitty, and revenge, patience and iudgment, as the 2. daughters of the great king, goe hand in hand: <hi>his mercy &amp; truth do meete togither, his righteouſnes and peace doe kiſse each other.</hi> Mercy going before with a <hi>pax vobis,</hi> peace vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that accept it: iudgement following after with a <hi>vae vobis</hi> woe vnto them that refuſe it, the one comming with an open boſome to receiue the penite<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t: the other following with a drawn ſword to devour the hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>harted. Mercy is firſt offered to leaue the wicked inexcuſable: iudgme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t is laſt exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted to deſtroy the wicked that are cul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable. For this is the vſual courſe which God taketh with the ſons of men: firſt to try them a good ſpace by gentle forbea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:4884:27"/>which if it draw them not vnto re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, then his arrowes of vengeance are readie prepared for deſtruction. So did he deale with the old world: hee ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red it an hundred &amp; twentie yeares, but <hi>when hee ſaw that the wickednes of man was great in the earth, &amp; that al the ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of the thoughts of his hart were onely evill continually.</hi> Gen. 6.5. Hee did by a mightie flowd deſtroy <hi>everie thing that was on the earth from man to beaſt.</hi> Gen. 7.23. So did hee deale with the fig. tree in the Goſpel, he ſpared it 3. whole years togither, and ſuffered it to be <hi>dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged &amp; dunged</hi> carefully: but continuing it ſelfe barren, &amp; making alſo the grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d barren round about it, the Lorde wil no lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger beare with it, it muſt be deſtroied, <hi>it muſt be cut downe.</hi> Luk. 13.7. So did he deale with thoſe <hi>Aegyptians</hi> of old, he ſent <hi>Moſes</hi> &amp; <hi>Aaron</hi> to inſtruct them, who wrought diverſe ſignes and mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles among them to win them to repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance: whereof when none could moue them, or pierce their hardned heartes,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:4884:27"/>they vvere quite over-whelmed in the midſt of the ſea, Exod. 14.27. So did he deale with his owne cittie, hee ſent Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets &amp; teachers early &amp; late, to wooe her to Chriſt as the ſpouſe to her bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grome, he ſent his owne ſonne to winne her from her ſin: but when ſhee woulde bee gathered by none of theſe, <hi>beholde her houſe vvas lefte vnto her deſolate.</hi> Luk. 13.35. Finally ſo doeth hee deale with <hi>Niniveh</hi> in my text, he giveth her ful 40. <hi>daies</hi> for her probation and triall: wherein if ſhee forſake not her ſinnefull waies, and turne vnto the Lord, there ſhal not a day or houre be further ſpent, vntill the iudgement of her overthrow be pronounced, <hi>and Niniveh ſhalbe de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtroyed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now the greatnes of this iudgment, is here further amplified, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the place againſt which it is denounced, beeing <hi>Niniveh,</hi> no petty towne of the nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, no obſcure place of the worlde, no little village or hamlet of the Eaſt, no ſmal citty in <hi>Aſsyria,</hi> as <hi>Bethlem</hi> was in
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:4884:28"/>
               <hi>Iuda:</hi> but <hi>a greate and excellent city of three daies iourney,</hi> even then one of the greateſt citties in the world. For as <hi>Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorus Siculus</hi> in his 3. lib. and 1. cap. <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rodotus</hi> in his <hi>Clio</hi> and <hi>Strabo</hi> in the 16. of his Geography haue at large deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed, thi <hi>Niniveh</hi> was 400. and 80. fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs in circuit. wheras <hi>Babylon,</hi> which <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> in his politicks calleth rather <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> a country then a city, had almoſt fewer by one hundred. And ſome haue beene of opinion that afterwardes as it grew in wealth, ſo it was much more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larged. Her wals were in height an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred feete, in breadth ſufficiently cape<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to receaue three carts on a row, in compaſſe 400. miles, adorned with a thouſand &amp; fiue hundred towers, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the height of every on was two hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred feete a peece. The buildings of it very faire, beeing (as ſome haue noted) eight whole yeares a rayſing vp, &amp; not by fewer at once then tenne thouſande workemen. The ſtate of it very comme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable, beeing ruled by a <hi>king and his no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:4884:28"/>Ion.</hi> 3.7. The people of it almoſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numerable, ſeeing there were <hi>ſix ſcore thouſand infa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, that could not diſcerne betweene their right hand and their left. Ion.</hi> 4.11. In a word if J name but <hi>Nini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veh</hi> I then name al, a <hi>beautiful &amp; plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant</hi> city, as the Hebrew word whence it is deriued importeth. Not only <hi>a great citty</hi> as <hi>Moſes</hi> calleth it, <hi>Gen.</hi> 10.12. but <hi>a great &amp; excellent city, or a citty great vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God,</hi> as our Prophet calleth it, ô here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in is the iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t aggravated! This ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent and famous and renowned <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niveh,</hi> this large and ſpacious &amp; popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous <hi>Niniveh,</hi> this faire and glorious &amp; goodly <hi>Niniveh ſhalbe deſtroyed. Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niveh</hi> that imperial commaunder of all the Eaſterne partes, that lifted her head aboue the nations, that dwelt in confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence and ſaid, I am and there is none beſides me, <hi>Niniveh ſhalbe deſtroied. Niniveh</hi> in times paſt highly renown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, prowde of her wals and bul-warks, puft vp in the wealthines of her inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants, &amp; the goodlines of her buildings,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:4884:29"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:4884:29"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:4884:30"/>
               <hi>Niniveh ſhal be destroyed. Niniveh</hi> the mother city of <hi>Aſsyria,</hi> the <hi>Metro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>polis</hi> of the Country, the golden heade of the picture, the glory of the earth, the ſeat of the Empire, the Lady of the Eaſt, the Queene of nations, the riches of the world, <hi>Niniueh ſhalbe deſtroied.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiection. </seg>
               </label> But ſome man peradventure wil ſay, what ſinnes hath <hi>Niniueh</hi> committed; how hath ſhee offended God: that ſhee ſo great and excellent, ſo famous &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowed citty, ſhould haue ſo ſevere a iudgment, denounced againſt her from the Lord? <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwere. </seg>
               </label> For anſwere whervnto J muſt confeſſe that the ſinnes, for which <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niveh</hi> is here ſo threatned, are not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed in my text, but elſe where ſet downe by the ſpirit of God. That this ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty was given to idolatry, it appeareth in the ſecond booke of Kings where it is ſaid that <hi>Senacherib was worſhipping his falſe God, in the temple of Niniveh, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his two ſonnes ſlew him.</hi> 2. <hi>King.</hi> 19.37, And if yee looke but into the third chap. of the Prophecy of <hi>Nahum;</hi> you ſhall
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:4884:30"/>finde other ſins of this cittie there rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>koned vp by the prophet. For he calleth it <hi>a mistreſse of witchcrafts, a bloudy cit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, full of lies &amp; robbery, from whence the pray departeth not.</hi> Vnto which ſinnes, J may alſo adde the ſinnes of infidelity, &amp; gluttonie, and pride, which I doe the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther iudge to be general faultes among them: becauſe in their repentance (as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>none by Gods grace ye ſhall hear) men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is made of ſuppreſſing theſe ſinnes, of ſuppreſſing their infidelitie, <hi>by belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving in God,</hi> of ſuppreſſing their glutto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <hi>by proclaiming a faſt,</hi> of ſuppreſſing their pride <hi>by putting on ſack-cloath fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the greateſt vnto the leaſt.</hi> But that one place is inſteede of al the reſt, to declare the ſinne of <hi>Niniveh,</hi> it is in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of this prophecie of <hi>Ionas:</hi> where it is ſaid that the wickednes of this peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple vvas come vppe before the Lorde, where the name of <hi>VVickednes</hi> in the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginal (as the learned note) ſignifieth the greateſt extremity that can be, and is not reſtrained to this or that ſin one
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:4884:31"/>of a thouſand, but is a moſt abſolute, &amp; all ſufficient terme, to al manner of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pietie.</p>
            <p>Thus then you ſee (moſt deare and bleſſed brethren, beloued in the Lorde Ieſus) that it is not for a ſmale thing, or matter of light mome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t: but for many &amp; moſt grievous ſins, even the height of al impietie, for which <hi>Niniveh</hi> this nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble citty muſt be deſtroyed. For howſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever her ſtate was moſt powerfull, her gouernment moſt excellent, her wals moſt ſtatelie, her towers moſt high, her citizens moſt wealthy, her name moſt renowned, her people almoſt innume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable: yet nether the mightines of her ſtate nor the excellencie of her gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, nor the climing of her wals, nor the aſpiring of her towers, nor the riches of her citizens, nor the honor of her name, nor the multitude of her people, if ſhee once giue over her ſelfe to ſin; can make her ſecure from the wrath of God. For greatnes of ſins wil ſhake the foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the greateſt citties, and multitude
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:4884:31"/>of offences wil diminiſh and conſume whole multituds of men. <hi>Iericho the ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of palme-trees</hi> as ſhe is called. Deut. 34.3. beeing withal a wicked and vncir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ciſed citty, idolatrous in the worſhip of God, and hoſtile to his people, had a lamentable ende. For loe the men of armes, at the Lords appointment, vtter<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly deſtroied al that was in it, <hi>both man &amp; woman, young and olde, beaſts and cattel, oxen &amp; aſses, with the edge of the ſword,</hi> Ioſ. 6.21. Tyrus <hi>was rich with the ſeed of</hi> Nilus <hi>that brought her abundance, the harueſt of the rivers were her revenews, and ſhee a mart of the nations, it was a glorious city, and her antiquity of anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent daies: ſhee crowned men and her mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants were Princes, &amp; her chapmen the nobles of the world. Eſ.</hi> 23. Yet beholde the iudgme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of the Lord, againſt that city for her ſins, as it is in the ſame chap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter: it was tould her, that <hi>her owne feete ſhould lead her a far of to be a ſoiourner: for the Lorde of hoſtes had decreed it, to staine the pride of all glory, and to bring
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:4884:32"/>to contempt al the honorable in the earth.</hi> Nô <hi>was full of people, and lay in the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, and had the waters rounde about it: whoſe ditch was the ſea, &amp; her wall was from the ſea yet, for her ſins, was ſhee ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried away, and went into captivity: her young childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> were daſhed in peeces at the head of the ſtreets, and they caſt lots for her noble men, and al her mighty men were bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d in chaines, Nahum.</hi> 3.10. Yea <hi>Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon</hi> called a great <hi>citty</hi> as wel as <hi>Nini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veh,</hi> that ſaid in her hart, <hi>I ſit as Queene, I am no widdow, &amp; ſhall ſee no mourning:</hi> by reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of her iniquities hath her iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment pronouned by the angel: <hi>It is fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len, it is fallen, &amp; is become the habitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Divels and the hole of all foule ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites, and the cage of every vncleane and hateful bird. Revel.</hi> 18.2. Nay <hi>Ieruſaleus though the perfection of beauty, and ioye of the whole earth, Lament.</hi> 2.15. Though ſhee were as deare vnto the LORDE as the ſignet on his right hand, and the onely ſpowſe of the greate king of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven: yet becauſe ſhee became wanton,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:4884:32"/>and played the harlot, and would not be reclaimed: ſhee was made a ſpectacle of vengance &amp; iudgment to all the coaſts of the earth &amp; natio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of the world. <hi>That ſanctified city that choſen citty of the Lord, that citty built in vnity, the Queene &amp; Empreſse of the Provinces,</hi> was ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faced, and leveled with the ground, that not one ſtone was left ſtanding vpon an other, neither in their houſes, wals, bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warkes, turrets, nor in the altars, ſanctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ary, or temple, the old, the young, the matrones, the virgins, the infantes, the princes, the prieſts, the Prophets, &amp; the Nazerites were al ſlaine, famiſhed, fet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered, ſcattered abroad, &amp; vtterly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed. For further knowledge of all which, J referre you to <hi>Ioſephus de bello Iudaico</hi> where theſe things are largely ſet downe; and he that readeth that ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry with dry eies, I wil ſay that his hart is harder then the hardeſt adamant, and himſelfe leſſe compaſſionate then the moſt barbarous <hi>Scythian</hi> in the world. <hi>Si ſit in viridi quid fiet in arido?</hi> If this
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:4884:33"/>be done in the greene tree, what ſhalbe done in the dry? <hi>Luk.</hi> 23.31. If the Lord dealt ſo ſeverelye with the <hi>Iewes</hi> that were the natural branches: what will he doe vnto them that are but the <hi>wilde branches? Rom.</hi> 11.21. And if he brought ſo heavy a deſtruction vpon his own ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty for ſin: then let not this famous citty of <hi>London</hi> flatter her ſelfe in her ſecuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: but let her, and all the citties of the world feare and tremble, leaſt commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the like ſinnes, the Lord bring vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the like iudgme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts. For as his mercy is comfortable: ſo is his iudgment ine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitable, and they that wil not with <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niveh</hi> imbrace him in the on, in accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the time of 40 <hi>daies,</hi> to their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion; ſhal vndoubtedly feele him in the other, in receiuing a perpetual iudg<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment to their confuſion. And ſo much be ſpoken concerning this ſecond cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtaunce, of the firſt general parte. which was Gods iudgment, denoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing deſtruction againſt <hi>Niniveh,</hi> if in the time allotted, ſhe would not amend.</p>
            <q>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:4884:33"/> 
               <hi>And Niniveh ſhalbe deſtroyed.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>Now lett vs ſee, what further vſe &amp; applicatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we may make of theſe things vnto our ſelves.</p>
            <p>Jhad thought (Right Honorable,<note place="margin">Application of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines.</note> right worſhipfull &amp; dearly beloued in Chriſt Ieſus) when I firſt made choice of this text to haue applied this ſermon of <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas</hi> to this renowned city of <hi>London</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>Metropolu</hi> of al <hi>England</hi> as <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niveh</hi> was of <hi>Aſſyria,</hi> becauſe in my ſimple iudgment this argument heere handled may very wel befit this place &amp; theſe times. But conſidering with my ſelfe that many of this greate aſſembly are inhabitants of other places of this land, I doe rather thinke it beſt to apply it to the people of <hi>England</hi> in general; that what is ſpoken of them, every man in particular may accompt as ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to himſelfe. And here, beloued, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede according to our Prophets me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod. If ever there were nation or king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome vnder the cope of heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Lord hath manifeſted himſelfe to
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:4884:34"/>be a God of much patience &amp; long ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering: ſurely ours is that nation, ours is that kingdome. How hath hee deſired <hi>Englands</hi> ſalvation,<note place="margin">Gods mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies to England.</note> how hath he waited for her converſion, how hath he ſought to win and wooe her to contrition? He hath ſent her not one <hi>Ionas,</hi> one time, but many hundred Prophets and tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, daily and howrely to call her to repentance. He hath giuen her not 40. <hi>daies</hi> as he did <hi>Niniveh,</hi> but full forty yeares and more to bethinke her ſelfe: vnder the peaceable governement of a moſt gracious ſoveraigne. Neuer did any father ſo long indure, the vntoward lineſſe of a wicked ſonne, neuer did anie Prince ſo long ſuffer, the rebellions of a diſloyall ſubiect, neuer did any Lorde ſo long forbear, the puniſhment of a neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent ſervant, never did any huſband ſo long ſuſtaine the iniuries of a levvde-li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving wiſe, as hee our gracious father, hath done vs prodigal ſonnes, as he our heauenly king, hath done vs vnnarural ſubiects, as he our mightie Lorde, hath
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:4884:34"/>done vs careleſſe ſervants, as he our lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving huſbande, hath done vs faithleſſe wines. His mercie &amp; forbearance to the <hi>Iſraclits,</hi> was nothing, in reſpect of that he hath ſhewed to vs the people of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi> He hath delivered vs from the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual darkneſſe of <hi>Aegypt,</hi> the palpable obſcuritie of ignorance and ſuperſtitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. He hath appointed vs his laws and ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, his ſtatutes and his commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. He hath given vs <hi>Manna</hi> from heaues, angels foode, the bread of our ſouls, the word of life, wher with he hath fed vs theſe manie yeares. But as the young hinds in <hi>Iob, beeing once growne ſat with corne goe from their dams, and returne not to them againe. Iob.</hi> 39.7. So wee being fatted and repleniſhed vvith theſe and a thouſand the like vnſpeake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able benefites and bleſſings forget and forſake the Lord of heauen. Witnes our vnthankefulneſſe and diſobedience, our grudging and murmuring againſt our maker. Witnes our cold zeale and luke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warmenes in our profeſſion, witnes our
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:4884:35"/>backſliding from the truth, our neglect &amp; contempt of the word of God. VVit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes the burden of innumerable ſins, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der which our land groaneth: enmity &amp; diſſention, fraud and diſſimulation, co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetouſnes and oppreſſion, pride &amp; am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition, aduſterie and fornication, ſvvea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring and forſwearing, lying and ſtealing &amp; the like, al which had long ſince pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led downe the heavy wrath of God and his iuſt iudgements vpon vs: had not his mercy and loving kindneſſe hindred the ſame. Let vs not (my deare brethren) to farre provoke this gracious and loving God, vvhom wee haue already grieued more then 40. yeares by our iniquities. You know that <hi>pride, &amp; fulnes of bread, aboundance of idlenes, and no ſtretching forth of handes vnto the poore,</hi> vvere the very capital and head ſinnes, which did even vvreſt and wring from the Lorde, his heavie and fearefull iudgment on <hi>Sodome</hi> and <hi>Gomor.</hi> Ezech. 16.49. And yet who doeth not know, that all theſe ſinnes, and infinite other, doe in as bad
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:4884:35"/>manner, and no leſſe meaſure, reigne &amp; revel in <hi>England</hi> what other ſequele the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is to be feared, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that the Lord ſhould ſhower downe his plagues and iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments vpon vs, in as great meaſure as e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver he did vpon the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? For he is the ſame God now, as he was then, and his harted ro ſin is ſtil the ſame. We read of three greivous puniſhments, which the Lord threatneth to bring vpon his people for their ſinnes <hi>I wall conſume them,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>by peſtilence, by famine, and by the ſword</hi> ſer. 14:12. Beloued in Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus,<note place="margin">Gods iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments ruſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected on England, if it doe not ſpeedily re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent.</note> let not <hi>England</hi> ſlatter her ſelfe any longer with the Lords patience, for ſhee hath provoked him to long. Beholdnow the axe of this anger is put to the root of the tree, his fan is in his land to purge his flore, his fire is kindled, his bow is rea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dy bent, the arrows of his vengance are ready drawn to the head, &amp; the ful viols of his diſpleaſure hangs over our heades ready, to power downe the like or grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter iudgments vpon vs: if wee ſpeedely turn not vnto him, by a true &amp; vnfained
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:4884:36"/>repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce.<note place="margin">The great plague in England 1593. See Stowes Cronicle.</note> The yeares are not yet many, nor the time long, ſince the inſcriptions on your dores without, were as evident teſtimonies of the deſtroying Angel of the Lord within: ſince <hi>the arrow that fli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth by day, the peſtilence that vvalketh in the darkneſse &amp; the plague that deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth at noone day,</hi> devoured many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands in this citty, &amp; other places of this land. And had not Gods mercy bin the greater, in ſaying then to his Angel, as in like caſe we read he did: <hi>it is ſufficient hould new thy hand</hi> 2. Sam. 24.16. A ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> might haue wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dred about our conntry, as <hi>Diogenes</hi> ſometimes did about <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens,</hi> with a candle and lanterne in his ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d at noone-day: to ſeeke, I do not ſay, a good ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at al, &amp; not haue fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d him.<note place="margin">The great dearth. 1597</note> The yeares are not yet many, nor the time longe, ſince the huſband<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as the prophet ſpekaeth <hi>ſowed much and brought in little, ſince the heavens o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver vs ſtayed themſelves fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dew, &amp; the earth vnder vs brought not forth her fruites, ſince the ſtaffe of our bread vvas
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:4884:36"/>broken. &amp; cleanes of teeth fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>din alour villages, &amp; want of victuals in alour cit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties.</hi> And had not Gods mercy bin the greater then vnto vs in ſending a plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful increaſe: <hi>our skin had cleaved to our bones, &amp; withered like a ſtock</hi> Lament.<note place="margin">The Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh fleete 1588.</note> 4.8. Finally the yeares are not yet many, nor the time longe, ſince the ſword of a forraine foe, hath bin ſhaken at our la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, threatning an overthrowe of the ſame: ſince tidings of warres, &amp; rumors of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifold troubls, haue bin ſounded in our eares: to ſay nothing of our wicked at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts &amp; diveliſh conſpiracies of many of our vnnatural countri-men at home. But ô Lord as thou haſt given but abad ſucceſſe to ſuch evil interprizes: ſo wee beſeech thee ſtil to bring to nought the proiects &amp; purpoſes of al ſuch either for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raine adverſaries that ſeeke our realmes deſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or trecherous <hi>Abſolons</hi> that lift vp their handes, againſt their dread ſoveraigne, &amp; thine anointed. Let vs not thinke (my deare brethren) that theſe iudgme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of peſtilence, of famine, &amp; the
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:4884:37"/>ſword, haue come vnto vs by chaunce, &amp; ſo gon away againe: There is a God above, that in ſome meaſure hath made vs taſt of them for our ſins: whom if we ſtil provoke, by heaping ſin vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſin, aſſu redly he hath theſe, &amp; greater plagues in ſtore, to power down vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs. For the arme of the Lorde is not ſhortened: hee that hath ſtriken vs once, can, &amp; wil, for our ſins, ſtrike the ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d time. He that hath ſmot ſome few of our nation with the ſword, can, &amp; wil, for our diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, if we repent not in time, with the ſword againe, deſtroy many thouſands and millions more. Hee that, with the plague of peſtile<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, hath take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> away here &amp; there on, can, &amp; wil, for our vntha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>k<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes, if wee repent not in time, with the ſame, or a greater diſeaſe take away<note n="*" place="margin">The la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentable experience of this wee feele in this yeare 2603.</note> whole multituds togither, nay devour whole citties, and towns, and leave our land as deſolate as a wildernes. He that hath puniſhed our bodis in the time of dearth for want of bread, can, &amp; wil for our rebellion, if we repent not in time,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:4884:37"/>ſuffer our ſoules to periſh for wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual comfort: yea he will bring on our land, as the Prophet ſpeaketh, <hi>not a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine of bread, but of hearing the word of the Lord, And wee ſhal wander from ſea to ſea, and from the North eve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto the Eaſt ſhal wee runne to &amp; fro, to ſeeke the word of the Lord, and ſhal not finde it.</hi> Amos 8.11 12. A heavy iudgment of al other (my deare brethren) &amp; yet moſt vſual, where Gods word is contemned &amp; ſet at naught. Great was the glory, &amp; glorious the light, which the Church of God ſometimes had in <hi>Aſia</hi> the leſſe, at what time the bleſſed Eva<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geliſt S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Iohn &amp; Policarpus,</hi> &amp; many other ſchollers of the Apoſtles flooriſhed there. How fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous for the word preached were thoſe citties of <hi>Graecia,</hi> floriſhing Churches of <hi>Corinth, Galatia, Epheſus, Philippi, Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſse, and Theſſalonica,</hi> wherin <hi>S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Paule</hi> preached, &amp; planted ſo many holeſome doctrines of the Chriſtian faith: and to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he wrote ſo many divine Epiſtles extant in our church to this day! But for
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:4884:38"/>the ſinnes &amp; iniquities, of the inhabita<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ta of thoſe places, were not the bright ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning lamps of religion quite extingui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed among them, was not the light of the Goſpell quite taken from them and ſince removed into the Weſt? Nay the citty <hi>Rome</hi> was once the mirrour of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, the glory of the world, the wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der of the Weſt, the ſanctuary of religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the very habitation of true piety, when <hi>her faith was publiſhed throughout the whole worlde,</hi> Rom. 1.8. But when religious <hi>Rome</hi> once proved beaſtly <hi>Babylon,</hi> the holy cittie an harlot, when idolatrie and ſuperſtition began once to rule &amp; raign in her: beholde her candleſticke was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved into the northerne parts, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the reſt to vs of this land: where if wee giue it no better welcome &amp; enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they did, how may we not iuſtly feare the like iudgement: leaſt the Lord deprive vs of ſo great a bleſſing, &amp; giue it to <hi>Tartarians</hi> and <hi>Moores</hi> wilde and ſavage people, that wil with greater alacrity receive it, &amp; peradventure with
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:4884:38"/>greater fruit entertaine it, then we haue done.</p>
            <p>Wherefore (my deare brethren) yet the word of the Lord is amongſt vs, yet the Prophets are in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> yet the pearle is in our field, yet the ſound of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel is heard throughout our land: O the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> let vs make more reckoning &amp; account of it, then heretofore we haue done: leſt this ſunne be defaced, leſt this light bee put out, leaſt it be told vs, as it was tolde the Angell of the Church of <hi>Epheſus, that our candle ſticke ſhalbe removed, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel.</hi> 2.5. Leaſt the Arke of God bee ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from vs, as it was from the <hi>Iſraelits,</hi> 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 4.12. Leaſt as <hi>Paule</hi> and <hi>Barna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bas</hi> ſaide to the <hi>Iewes: to you is the worde of this ſalvation ſent, but ſeeing yee put it from you, loe wee turne vnto the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles, Act.</hi> 13.46. So the Lord ſay vnto <hi>England</hi> to thee ô <hi>England</hi> haue J given my worde but becauſe thou haſt caſt it away from thee, &amp; iudgeſt thy ſelfe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy of everlaſting life, loe J will take it away, and giue it to a barbarous nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:4884:39"/>
               <hi>that ſhal bring forth the fru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>its ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, Math.</hi> 21.43. Yet the Lord offereth his grace vnto vs: O then let vs accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to <hi>S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Augustines</hi> Councel in tract. 33. <hi>in Iohan.</hi> Vſe it now if we wil vſe it at all: Leaſt the gate of mercy, which to day is open, to morrow be ſhut, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver opened againe vnto vs! Yet the meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers &amp; Miniſters of God doe <hi>beſeech vs for Chriſt his ſake to be reconciled to him:</hi> O then let vs now become newe men in the Lord, leaſt a heavier iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment light vpon vs! Yet the daies of ple<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ty are amongſt vs: O then let vs nowe with <hi>Ioſeph</hi> lay vp in ſtore, leaſt wee die in the famine! Yet the ſeaſon is calme &amp; the weather faire: O then let vs nowe with <hi>Noah</hi> build vp an arke, leaſt with the reſt we periſh in the flowde! <hi>Gen.</hi> 7.21. Yet the Angell tarieth at the gates of <hi>Sodome:</hi> O then let vs now with <hi>Lot</hi> departe thence, and haſt away with the Angell, leaſt with that wicked people wee be deſtroyed! <hi>Gen.</hi> 19.24. Yet the bridgroome taryeth and waiteth for vs
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:4884:39"/>O then let vs make haſt to enter in with him to mariages ſole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nity: leaſt with the fooliſh Virgins, we be repelled, with <hi>a non novi vos, I know you not! Mat.</hi> 25.12. Yet wiſdome crieth in our ſtreeres <hi>vſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> quo?</hi> O how long wil yea love vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty? O then let vs nowe ſeeke vnto her, leaſt, ſeeking hereafter, we ſeek in vain, <hi>and ſhee laugh at our deſtruction! Prou.</hi> 1.26. Yet the Lord ſetteth open his ſtore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe of mercy: O then let vs now run to him for a bleſſing, leaſt, <hi>comming too late with Eſau, we finde none though we ſeeke it with teares! Heb.</hi> 12.17. Yet the Lord knocketh at the dore of our harts: O then let vs now open vnto him: leaſt hee ſaie to vs as he did to <hi>Ieruſalem, O that thou hadſt knowne at the leſt in this thy day the things that belonge vnto thy peace, but now they are hid fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thee! Luk.</hi> 19 42, Yet the Lord cryeth vnto vs to a mend: O then let vs, in this acceptable time of grace, harken vnto him, leaſt he ſay of vs, as he did of a hard harted peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: <hi>as I haue cryed to you, and you woulde
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:4884:40"/>not heare me, ſo a time ſhal come when ye ſhal cry vnto me, and I wil not he are you.</hi> Zach. 7.13. Yet the Lord calleth vs vnto him: O then let vs nowe come, leaſt, if we come hereafter, it be too late: <hi>as Ioab came to Abſolon, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his barly fields were burnt.</hi> 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 14.31. Yet the Lord wai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth for our returne from <hi>Babylon:</hi> O the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> let vs now returne vnto him, while wee haue time, leaſt hereafter he ſay to vs as the <hi>Angel ſware there ſhalbe no more time Revel.</hi> 10.6. Yet the Lord wooeth <hi>England &amp; London,</hi> as he did <hi>Ephraim</hi> and <hi>Iuda:</hi> O <hi>England</hi> what ſhal I do vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee, O <hi>London</hi> how ſhal I intreate thee? O then let vs <hi>imbrace the riches of his bountifullneſſe,</hi> &amp; his exceeding pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience: leaſt wee <hi>heape vnto our ſelues wrath againſt the day of wrath, &amp; of the declaration of the iuſt iudgment of God Rom.</hi> 2.5. Finally yet the Lord, by <hi>Ionas,</hi> cryeth in the ſtreets of <hi>Niniveh,</hi> &amp; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny hundred <hi>Ionaſses</hi> in the Citties and townes of <hi>England, yet</hi> 40. <hi>daies,</hi> and, if yee wil not repent, not only <hi>Niniveh</hi>
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:4884:40" rendition="simple:additions"/>but the reſt of the land alſo ſhalbe <hi>quite defaced:</hi> O then let vs al, with <hi>Niniveh</hi> in my text, repent vs of our ſinnes, <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue in God. proclaime a faſt, and put on ſackcloth,</hi> leaſt this heavy iudgment denounced by our Prophet againſt <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niveh</hi> iuſtly fal on vs for our tranſgreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. And ſo much concerning my firſt general part which was <hi>Ionas Sermon</hi> to the <hi>Ninivits</hi> with the application ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of vnto our ſelues. Now followeth the conſideration of the ſecond parte in the next words, to wit the <hi>Ninivites repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taunce;</hi> wherof a word or two and ſo I will commit you to God:</p>
            <q>So the people of Niniveh beleeued God, proclaimed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> fast. &amp;c:</q>
            <p>Heere is the fruite and effect which this Sermon wrought in the <hi>Ninivites,</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed as I toulde you before in theſe 4. circumſtances, 1. By their faith, which was not fruitleſſe <hi>ſoe the people of Nini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veh beleeued God</hi> 2. By their faſting, which was not private, <hi>and proclaimed a faſt,</hi> 3, By their attire, which was not
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:4884:41"/>coſtly, <hi>and put on ſackcloth,</hi> 4. By their number, which were not few, <hi>from the greateſt to the leaſt.</hi> The leaſt of which 4 circumſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces, if I might dwel vpon the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, would require a longer time, then is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lotted mee for the handling of them all. And J muſt confeſſe that my meditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons haue beene ſo farre inlarged in this ſecond point, that (the time beeing al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt paſt and the weather ſo ſodainely vnſeaſonable) I ſhall not now deliver, without offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding your patience, the on quarter of that which I had purpoſed. How be it becauſe I perceiue no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirous to depart, but everie one willing to ſtay, and ſo ſettle himſelf vnto atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: J wil be bold to point at thoſe foure obſervatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, which are included in this ſecond part: breifly running them al o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, <hi>tanquam Canis in Nilo lambe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s,</hi> pic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king here and there a litle, as may moſt befit this auditory and theſe times, lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the conſideration of the reſt to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very mans private meditation.<note place="margin">Obſer. 1.</note>
            </p>
            <q>
               <hi>So the people of Niniveh beleeued God.</hi>
            </q>
            <pb n="71" facs="tcp:4884:41"/>
            <p>That is, they did beleeue <hi>Ionas</hi> ſermon to be as true, and the iudgment therein denounced to be as certaine, if they did not repent, as if God himſelfe had ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken it vnto them. Thus <hi>faith commeth, by hearing, &amp; hearing by the word of God, Rom.</hi> 10.17. A notable ground-worke &amp; ſure foundation of their repentaunce, <hi>quo ſublato, omne quod ſuper ſtruitur de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruitur adificium.</hi> VVhich being taken away and remoued, in vaine and to no purpoſe do we build vp our ſelus in ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctity of life, and ſinceritie of converſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. For as the bleſſed Apoſtle ſpeaketh, <hi>Hee that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth to God muſt firſt beleeue that God is, Heb,</hi> 11.6. <hi>VVithout this faith it is vnpoſsible to pleaſe God, &amp; what ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver is not of this faith is ſin. Rom.</hi> 14.23. By how much the more it augmenteth the commendation of theſe <hi>Ninivites</hi> whoſe faith was the firſt ſtone in their ſpiritual building, their firſt ſtep in their Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> race, their firſt link in their gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> chaine of Chriſtianity, the firſt ſigne of their new converſion, the firſt degree
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:4884:42"/>in their holy converſation, the firſt ron<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d in their <hi>Iacobs</hi> ladder, wher by they aſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vp into the preſence of the Lorde a ſtra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge &amp; a wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>derful matter, that is here ſaid of this heathniſh &amp; idolatrous peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of <hi>Niniveh,</hi> that <hi>they beleeved God.</hi> Where ſome thing was expected, there nothing is to be fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, &amp; where nothing was looked for, behold great abou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce: the fatted ſoile is become barre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and the barten ground be areth much encreaſe, the natural oliue is withered away &amp; the wild oliue is become fruitfull: the natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral vine hath no grapes, &amp; the baſtarde vine beareth many cluſters. <hi>Credidit Ni niveh, &amp; I ſraell incredulus perſeverat, credidit praputiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, et circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ciſio manet in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidelis,</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Ierome</hi> vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this place. <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas</hi> had a long time preached to the <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelits,</hi> &amp; loe <hi>Iſrael</hi> was not <hi>Iſrael</hi> but a diſobedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t natio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. He preacheth but one ſermo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> among theſe <hi>Ninivits,</hi> &amp; he fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth more true <hi>Iſraelites</hi> among them the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in his own cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trey: the circumciſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſkorneth, and the vncircumciſion are
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:4884:42"/>made heires of the promiſes, the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren prooue rebels, and the rebels are chaunged into children, the <hi>Iewes</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temne the worde, and the <hi>Gentiles</hi> em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace it. The <hi>Iſraelits</hi> that were <hi>the elect of God, the ſonnes of Abraham, the heires of the covenant</hi> remaine vnfaithful: and the <hi>Ninivites</hi> that were <hi>Gentiles in the fleſh, that were called the vncircumciſion, alients from the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon wealth of Iſraell, ſtrangers from the covenant of promiſe,</hi> they are found faithful. <hi>So the people of Niniveh beiceved God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obſerv. </seg>2</label> Novve becauſe Faith without good vvorkes is but a <hi>dead faith, and the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils faith,</hi> as S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Iames</hi> calleth it. Jac. 2. Faith in them (which if it be a true faith is never ſolitary in any) bringeth foorth the good worke of faſting. <hi>They proclai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med a faſt.</hi> Faith leadeth the way as the miſtreſie, faſting a good worke is readie at hand, as the hand-maide. Faith as the foundation is firſt laide, faſting as the building is raiſed on it. Faith as the tree is firſt planted, faſting as the fruite
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:4884:43"/>groweth theron, faith goeth before as a cauſe of faſting, faſting followeth after as an effect of faith. <hi>And they proclai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med a faſt.</hi> Not a contentious <hi>fast,</hi> as their was, who <hi>faſted to ſtrife and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate</hi> Eſa. 58.4. Not an Hypocriticall <hi>faſt,</hi> as their was <hi>who diſfigured their faces, that they might be ſeene of men to faſt</hi> Mat. 6.16. Not a meritorious <hi>faſt,</hi> as their was, who had thought, by this meanes to haue <hi>merited ſomething at the hands of God</hi> Zach. 7.5. Not a ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitious <hi>faſt,</hi> as the <hi>faſt</hi> of the <hi>Papiſts</hi> is, who hold it noe leſſe then damnation, on certaine daies to cate the leaſt bit of fleſh: and yet at the ſame times they can be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tent, to epicurize it with the ſwee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt wines, hotteſt ſpices, dainteſt fruits, that forraine countries, and moſt deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious fiſh, thet the fartheſt ſeas can af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford-But the <hi>Faſt</hi> of <hi>Niniveh</hi> was an <hi>orderly faſt,</hi> it was <hi>a publike faſt,</hi> it was an <hi>abſolute faſt,</hi> it was a <hi>religious faſt. Orderly,</hi> becauſe not ſeditiouſly vnder ta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ken by the multitude, but deſigned and
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:4884:43"/>appointed by the King and his Nobles. <hi>Publike,</hi> becauſe proclaimed to be kept, not of this or that family, but of everie thing that breatheth among them both man and beaſt. <hi>Abſolute,</hi> becauſe they did not, with the <hi>Carthuſian</hi> monkes &amp; others of the like ſort, for beare fleſh, &amp; feede on dainty fiſh, and ſvvill in their booles of wine: but as it is in the 7. verſe of this chapter, they were forbid <hi>to taste anie thing at all. Religious,</hi> becauſe they were commanded in this their <hi>faſt, to turne from their evill wares &amp; from the wickednes of their hands.</hi> O what a wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy <hi>faſt</hi> vvas this, O vvhat a ſingular meanes to appeaſe the vvrath of God? <hi>Pliny</hi> in his 7. lib. and 2. chap. ſaith that <hi>faſting ſpittle is preſent death to ſerpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts.</hi> How true that is J know not. But of this I am ſure and certaine, that ſuch a <hi>faſte</hi> as this, (ſo ſolemnely vndertaken, ſo ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely performed,) cannot chuſe but be a great meanes, to weaken the power of the <hi>great Dragon the olde Serpent,</hi> and quench al the fierie dartes of the Devill
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:4884:44"/>as<note n="a" place="margin">Ardertes Diaboli fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gictae ieiu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niotum fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ore re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtringendae ſunt.</note> S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Ierome</hi> ſpeaketh. This is the fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of alother vertues as the ſame father<note n="b" place="margin">Ad De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me triadem virginem</note> calleth it. This is the deſtroyer of ſinnes, as<note n="c" place="margin">De Elia &amp; ieiunio.</note> 
               <hi>Ambroſe</hi> nameth it. This is the token of humility, and extinguiſher of luſts, as<note n="d" place="margin">Epiſt. 121. &amp; ſer. de ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>Avguſtine</hi> tearmeth it. This is the rooter out of all tranſgreſſions, as <hi>S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Bernard</hi> vſually defineth it. This is the tamer of the fleſh, as <hi>Gregory</hi> in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny places deſcribeth it. This is the expel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler of temptations, as <hi>Tertullian</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly ſpeaketh of it. This was the means which the <hi>Iſraelits</hi> vſed, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they were diſtreſled for the ſlaughter of their men by the <hi>Beniamites: they wept and faſted al the day vnto the evening</hi> Iudg. 20.26. this was the meanes which <hi>Iehoſhophat</hi> vſed, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his enimies came againſt him to battell: <hi>He proclaimed a fast through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all Iudah</hi> 2. Chro. 20.3. This was the means which <hi>David</hi> vſed, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his child was ſicke, <hi>he faſted and lay al night vpon the earth.</hi> 2. Sam, 12.16. Finally this was the meanes which the <hi>Ninivites</hi> vſed in my text being terrified with the iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:4884:44"/>denou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ced by the Prophet <hi>they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeued God, and proclaimed a faſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obſer. </seg>3</label> Now the 3 circumſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, that ſetteth down what effect this ſermon wrought in them, was their attire, which was not coſtly, <hi>they put on ſackcloth.</hi> Ahabit very fit to expreſle the humility of the mind, and well ioyned in this place to faſting. For theſe 2. are the <hi>weapons of repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tanc</hi> as<note n="e" place="margin">Saecus &amp; ieiunium at ma ſunt paenueti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> auxilae pec<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>catorum Hierom.</note> S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Ierome</hi> calleth them, And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the ſame father ſaith: <hi>conſequenter ad ieiunium ſaccam copulant, vt inanis venter, &amp; habitus luctuoſus, ambitioſiùs dominum deprecentur.</hi> They adde vnto faſting homely attire, therby to further their praiers, and to make themſelues more fit, to apply their ſuite vnto God. And wheras no doubte they had offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded God, both inwardly and outwardly: they doe herein ſhew the ſignes of their griefe, both within &amp; without. Within, by debarring their belly, &amp; ſtomackes, of their vſual ſubſtance, as they did by their abſolute abſtinence in their faſt. Without, by making that fleſhe which
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:4884:45"/>had taken delight before in bewty and bravery to be now baſely, and vgly clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed, with no better a garment the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſackcloth, wherin as <hi>Gregory in his</hi> 35. <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>moral</hi> noteth, is ſhewed a rough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes &amp; a pricking, even the compunctio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of our ſins: And <hi>Tertullia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> calleth it <hi>ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roris inſigne</hi> the very enſigne and badge of ſorrow: becauſe heretofore, in anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent time, they did vſe to weare it vppon ſuch occaſions. Witneſle the Patriarke <hi>Iacob,</hi> who, vpon the newes of his ſonne <hi>Ioſephes</hi> death, is ſaid <hi>to rent his clothes, to put ſackcloth about his loines, &amp; to ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row for his ſonne a long ſeaſon.</hi> Gen. 37.34. Witnes <hi>Mordechai,</hi> who, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the King had yeelded to the bloody requeſt of <hi>Haman,</hi> for murdering all the <hi>Iewes, put on ſackcloth &amp; aſhes, &amp; cryed a great cry and a bitter, in the midst of the citty.</hi> Heſt. 4.1. Witnes <hi>David,</hi> who, in ſign of his ſorrow for <hi>Abner,</hi> commaunded the people <hi>to rent their clothes, &amp; to put on ſackcloth.</hi> 2. Sam. 3.31. Witnes, in ſteed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> wherof J ſpeake,
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:4884:45"/>whoſe king roſe vp from his throne, and laid his robe from him, &amp; covered him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe with ſackcloth, &amp; ſat in duſt &amp; aſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, whoſe nobles followed him, woſe Commons imitated the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt to the loweſt, from the eldeſt to the youngeſt: fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the richeſt to the pooreſt, all were clade in ſackcloth &amp; baſe aray, as it followeth in the text, <hi>fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt to the leaſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obſer. </seg>4</label> The laſt circumſtance (for I cannot ſtand to amplifie any) wherin theſe <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nivets</hi> repentance is diſcribed, is taken from their nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber, which were not fewe, <hi>from the greateſt vnto the leaſt.</hi> For it is not one of a houſe, or ſome few of a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, or ſome of the better ſorte of the people, that thus were ready to humble themſelves before the Lord: but all in general, &amp; every on in particular, from the eldeſt father, to the youngeſt ſuck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, from the greateſt potentate to the meaneſt peyſant, of what ſex, eſtate, or conditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſoever they be, al are ready to further this holy duty. I might here iuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:4884:46"/>take occaſion to ſpeake of the duty of ſuperiour magiſtrats, vvho may be here vnderſtood by the <hi>greateſt,</hi> as alſo of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour ſubiectes, who are ſpecified by the <hi>least:</hi> how they ſhould, as at al times ſo eſpecially in the times of common ca<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lamities, with a mutual conſent, caſt down themſelues in a generall humilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion before the higheſt. But I can but point at this doctrine. Let it be ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t for our inſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that ſeeing theſe <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nivits</hi> did ſo vniverſally performe this, that without doubt, they ſhall riſe vp in iudgme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t againſt vs at the laſt day, if we be defectiue heere in having the like oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. For in their holy exerciſes, behold a pleaſant harmony &amp; agreement, <hi>ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ior aetas incipit, &amp; vſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ad minorem per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venit,</hi> ſaith a good father. The elder fort begin, and the younger they followe af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; the ſuperiours ſay to the inferiours, <hi>looke on mee and doe yee likewiſe.</hi> Iud. 7.17. And the inferiors anſwere the ſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riors, as the people did <hi>Ioſhua, al that yee commaund vs vvee will doe</hi> Ioſ. 1.16. In
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:4884:46"/>a worde, as according to Philoſophie in the natural bodie, the heart alone is not warme, but the heat thereof is a propa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gating heate, diffuſing it ſelfe in an or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly ſort to the reſt of the members, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven the hands and feet the moſt remote parts of the vvhole: ſo in the common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth of <hi>Niniveh,</hi> vvhich was abodie politicke, the Magiſtrates and gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners themſelues were not only through<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly warmed with the heate of devotion: but the common people alſo, and vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar ſorte did participate of that quality: and as the precious ointment vpon <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rons</hi> head <hi>ran downe by his bearde, to the skirts of his cloathing, Pſal.</hi> 133.2. So theſe notable effectes of <hi>beleeving God,</hi> and <hi>fasting,</hi> and <hi>putting on ſackcloath,</hi> were deriued from the king to his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell, and nobilitie, and from them to the meaneſt ſubiect. And as we read of the multitude of beleevers, that <hi>they were of one heart, and of one ſoule, Act.</hi> 4.32. So here was a general conſent, amonge a greater number of new converts: there
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:4884:47"/>was but one heart, and one ſoule, one minde, and one meaning, one faith and one faſt, one deſire, and on attire, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them al <hi>from the greateſt to the leaſt.</hi> O what a goodly ſight was this? O howe was it poſſible but that ſuch a general cry and conſent as this ſoe vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal a humiliation, ſhould be accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble vnto the Lord? For if he hath promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, <hi>that were two or three are gathered togither in his name, he wilbe in the midſt of them, Math.</hi> 18.20. How much more the, when ſo many thouſands of al eſtats conditions, aſſemble themſelves in ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting, ſackcloth, and praier, before their God in the great Congregation?</p>
            <p>Thus you ſee (Right Honorable, Right worſhipfull moſt deare and bleſſed bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren) what a plentiful harveſt, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth af a little ſeed ſowen, what goodly rivers iſhue from a little fountaine, what rare &amp; ſingular effects, are wrought in theſe <hi>Ninivits,</hi> by a few words ſpoken by the Prophet <hi>Ionas.</hi> Shall I here commende the Prophets eloque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, who, like a good
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:4884:47"/>oratour, did ſo rule and raigne in their minds, that as it was ſaid of <hi>Hercules Cel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticus,</hi> the eares of his auditors, were tied with a chaine, to the tip of his tongue? Or ſhall I attribute it to the ſoft, &amp; gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle diſpoſition of theſe <hi>Ninivites,</hi> vvho ſo eaſily yeelded at the ſou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets voice?<note place="margin">I his one general do<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ctrine iſhu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth from al the 4. parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars of this part.</note> Or rather ſhal I not here admire, at the powerfull operatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the word of God, that beeing delivered by the voice of on man, and that a ſtraun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, it ſhould make ſo great a king, ſoe ſtately nobles, ſo rich citizens, ſo many thouſand of barbarous &amp; heathen peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, to vaile bonnet, and to deſcende fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the throne of their pride, and to caſt downe themſelues, in faſting and ſack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloth before the Lord? Surely this is that word, which, like <hi>the ſnow &amp; rayn never returneth voide, but proſpereth in the thing wher vnto it is ſent. Eſ.</hi> 55.11. This is that word, which is the <hi>power of God vnto ſalvation. Rom.</hi> 1.16. This is that word, that is <hi>like a fire &amp; a hammer that breaketh the stone. Ier.</hi> 23 29. This
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:4884:48"/>is that word which is <hi>liuely and mighty in operation, ſharper then any two edged ſword, and entring thorough, even to the dividing a ſunder of the ſoule &amp; the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite, and of the ioints, and of the marrow, and is a diſcerner of the thoughts and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents of the hart Heb.</hi> 4.12. This is that worde, that <hi>is mightly through God, to caſt downe houldes and to overthrow everie high thing, that is exalted againſt the knowledg of God, and to bring into capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity every thought, to the obedience of Chriſt</hi> 2. <hi>Cor:</hi> 10.5. Finally this is that worde, which made the diſciples harts <hi>to burne within them,</hi> while they talked with Chriſt. <hi>Luk.</hi> 24.32. Which made <hi>Felix tremble, Act.</hi> 24.26. Which made the <hi>Iewes to be pricked in their hartes, Act.</hi> 2.37. Which made <hi>David</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe, he had <hi>ſinned againſt the Lord,</hi> 2. <hi>Sam,</hi> 12.13. Which made the <hi>people pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licans, and ſouldiers,</hi> aſke <hi>Iohn Baptiſt, what they ſhould doe. Luk.</hi> 3.14. Which made <hi>Ionas</hi> denounce deſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niveh,</hi> and <hi>Niniveh</hi> to repent, for feare
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:4884:48"/>of the deſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> denounced ſo the meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage of their overthrow, overthrew the meſſage, the prophecy fell, and the citty fel not, be cauſe her fal was prophecied. O <hi>newe and admirable thinge,</hi> (ſaith S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> in his 5. <hi>Hom. ad populum Antiochenum) the denu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ciation of death, hath brought forth life, the ſentence of the deſtruction, hath made a nullity in the ſente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce:</hi> ſuch is the vertue of Gods word, ſuch is the authority of his everlaſting truth.</p>
            <p>And is this even ſo? Jsthe word of the ſpirite ſo mightye in operation, hath it wrought ſo ſtrange effects, and brought forth ſuch wonderful fruites, in ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t people, to whom the Lord ſent but one Prophet, and that in ſo ſhorte a ſpace? How great then ſhal our iudgment be of this land, to whome the Lord in mercy hath ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſo many Prophets, &amp; teachers, theſe foure and forty yeares togither, to inſtruct vs, and to cal vs to repentance: and yet we lie ſtil frozen in the dregges of our iniquities? For if we doe but exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:4884:49"/>our ſelues by theſe <hi>Ninivits,</hi> vve ſhall finde that our repentance co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth farre ſhort of theirs. Doe we, in the firſt place, imitate the <hi>Ninivits</hi> faith <hi>in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeving of God?</hi> I know that many doe, &amp; God forbid there ſhoulde bee anye in a Chriſtian commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>-wealth, either ſo wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully ignorant, as not to beleeue, or ſo maliciouſly obſtinate, as not to confeſſe this truth: and yet there are not vvan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting amongſt vs, and they of great place alſo it is to bee feared, that ſaie vvith the foole in the Pſalme, <hi>There is no God at all.</hi> Thou damned Atheiſt, whoſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver thou art, lifte vp thine eies vnto the heavens, &amp; behold therein, the ſun, the moone, and the ſtars, the wonderful works of God. Caſt down thine eies vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the earth, and behold therein, trees, pla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, hearbs, flowers, beaſts, &amp; cattel: &amp; in them co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fider not the power of <hi>nature</hi> as thou fooliſhlie calleſt it, but of the God of nature, which framed &amp; faſhio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned all. Conſider the ebbing &amp; flowing of the ſea, and the wonderfull workes of
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:4884:49"/>the higheſt in the deepe. Looke into thy ſelfe <hi>a little worlde,</hi> how art thou faſhio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned behinde and before, within &amp; withe out, hovv wonderfully art thou made vvith varietie of faculties, diſtinction of members, proportion of body, to ſaie nothing of thy ſoule a heavenlie creature? And if al this, vvill not make thee confeſſe there is a God: yet knovve this, that the horrour of thy conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, for this thy ſo greate blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie, ſhall make thee, vvhether thou wilt or no, acknowledge this truth. Or if thy conſcience, bee ſeared with an hot yron in this world yet be thou well aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that the vvorme of conſcience, that never dyeth, in the worlde to come ſhal torment thee, in the lake that ever bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, and in the fire that neuer goeth out.</p>
            <p>Do we in the ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d place with theſe <hi>Ninivites</hi> betake our ſelues to <hi>faſting</hi> for our ſinnes? What then is the cauſe, that there are ſo many amongſt vs, who like thoſe voluptuous <hi>Princes</hi> of <hi>Iſraell,
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:4884:50"/>doe ſtretch themſelues vpon their beds of ivory, and cate the lambes of the flocke, &amp; the calues out of the ſtal, delighting them ſelues in the ſound of the violl, and other inſtruments of muſicke that drinke wine in boles, and annoint themſelves vvith ſweet ointments, not remembring the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of poore Ioſeph.</hi> Amos 6.6. Theſe are the <hi>Epicures</hi> of the world, who wil rather feaſT luxuriouſlie with dru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lofernes</hi> then faſt religiouſly with theſe godly <hi>Ninivites.</hi> Theſe are they, <hi>whoſe God is their bellie, vvhoſe glory is their ſhame,</hi> whoſe only felicitie conſiſteth in delicate fare: being of his minde in the hiſtory<note n="*" place="margin">Philoxe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus apud A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ianum de vatia hiſt. lib. <hi>10.</hi> cap <hi>9.</hi>
               </note> who ſaid of his meate: that <hi>that was the ſweeteſt which vvas the deereſt.</hi> But as the hiſtorian there very wel cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celleth <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Theſe examples muſt be remembred, not that any ſhould follow &amp; imitate them, but that every one ſhoulde abhorre and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt them.</p>
            <p>Thirdly do we imitate the <hi>Ninivites</hi>
               <pb n="89" facs="tcp:4884:50"/>attire, in clothing our ſelues in <hi>ſackcloth</hi> and courſe garments? Howe then com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth it to paſſe, that the vgly and dete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtable monſter pride, hath ſo over-run our land: that al eſtates, and degrees a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt vs, are ſo tainted &amp; infected with this blemiſh? Noble-men in the courte, Gentlemen in the country, ſerving men every where, vpſtart <hi>Swaggerers</hi> &amp; cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting <hi>Caveliers,</hi> who, when they haue no inward qualities to commend the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, they muſt haue the ivy buſh of long haire to hang over their ſhoulders; not regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Paules</hi> reproofe. 1. Cor. 11.14. nor <hi>Abſolons</hi> iudgement. 2. Sam. 18.9. Theſe are our inventors of newe faſhio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned garments, our <hi>French,</hi> our <hi>Turkiſh,</hi> our <hi>Spaniſh,</hi> our <hi>Italian</hi> Engliſh-men. For a man may ſee a liuely reſemblance of al theſe in their apparel: as if the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities of al nations, vvere little enough, to make vp the meaſure of an <hi>Engliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans</hi> pride. Let them not thinke, that want of other matter, hath driven vs to tax theſe follies in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. It is rather want
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:4884:51"/>of grace in them, that they will not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend. For if we ſhould not cry out a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt theſe their foul, &amp; filthy ſins they would, on day, cry out before the tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal ſeate of God, againſt them and vs. Good God, that the ſonns of <hi>Adam,</hi> ſhould ſo farre degenerate fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Adam!</hi> He good man wos content, with a garment of <hi>figg-tree leaues to hid bunakednes.</hi> Gen. 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. But we wil ſcarce be pleaſed with the rateſt, and richeſt workmanhip, that art or nature can af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foord, to cover our ſinful bodies. Nay as <hi>Plinie in his</hi> 5. <hi>lib. &amp; firſt chapter</hi> noted the riott and excelle of his time: ſo may we iuſtly do the like of outs. Becauſe forreſts are ſought out, farre and neere, for iuory and citron trees, and all the rocks of <hi>Gerulia</hi> are ſearched for ſhei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiſhes, that yeeld the purple crimſon co<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lour, to make our apparell ſhew glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous. <hi>But ô folly and vanity of advanities</hi> ſaith the ſame another, <hi>euer to think, o<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering our ſimple beginning, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we were ſent into the world, to line in pride, &amp; to
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:4884:51"/>adorne &amp; decke our carkeſses in braverie, that are nought but clay &amp; put refaction.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Finally do we with theſe <hi>Ninivites,</hi> in the laſt circumſtance, generally turne vnto the Lord, &amp; humble our ſelues be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him, <hi>fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the greateſt vnto the leaſt?</hi> what the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is the cauſe, that all of vs yong and old, high and low, haue ſo erred in our waies: everyone, <hi>turning into his own race, as the horſe ruſheth into the bat<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tle,</hi> to ſpeake with the Prophet? Ier. 8.6. What is the cauſe, that, in this bright ſunnſhine of the Goſpel, ſuch palpable darkeneſſe of errour &amp; ignorance, ſuch reliques of ſuperſtitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; idolatry, ſhould remaine amongſt vs? What is the cauſe that ſo many of vs, are meere <hi>tempori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing newters, luke warme profeſſors, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hote nor colde like them.</hi> Revel. 3.15. halting betweene two opinions, coldlie profeſſing the Religion eſtabliſhed, but in hart imbracing Papiſtical falſe-hood? What is the cauſe, that the <hi>Ieſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ites and Seminaries,</hi> finde ſuch ſecret favour a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt vs: who, like ſubtil deceavers, are
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:4884:52"/>at open warre on with another, but yet tyed to gither by the taſſe like <hi>Sampſons Foxes</hi> with fire brandes to deſtroy our Church? What is the cauſe that, after the Goſpel ſo long preached, holines of life is ſo little practiſed: that many come not at all to heare the worde of God or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming, with the <hi>deaſe adder</hi> they ſtop their eares at the ſou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d therof or hearing it, bring not forth the fruits of repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce: or repenting for a time, returne at le<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ght with the dog to his vomit, &amp; the ſwine vnto her filth? Laſtly what is the cauſe that our land is <hi>ful of adulterers, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of othes the land mourneth,</hi> to vſe the Prophets words Ier. 23.10. that vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye hath corrupted the rich cormorant, ambitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the proud Prelate, covetouſnes the greedy lawyer, diſdaine the ſcornful courtier, deceit the cunning artificer, &amp; the like. that all eſtates and degrees, are knowen by their ſeveral ſinnes, as every gentleman by his ſeveral cogniſance? Is this our vniverſall converſion vnto the Lord? is this the fruite of the Goſpel? are
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:4884:52"/>theſe the badges of our repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tance? Are theſe the effects, I ſay not of one ſermo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as <hi>Ionas</hi> his was to <hi>Niniveh,</hi> but of ſo many thouſand ſermons, delivered fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> time to time vnto vs?<note place="margin">Never more prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver leſſe pra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ing.</note> Beloved in Chriſt Ieſus, I am verely perſwaded, that the immortal ſeede of Gods word, was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver more plentiful ſowen ſince the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles time, then it hath bin amongeſt vs, theſe many yeares togitherithe Lord make vs thankfull for ſo great a bleſſing. And yet as <hi>Lictantius</hi> ſaid, <hi>there vvas never leſſe wiſdome in Greece, then in the time of the</hi> 7. <hi>wiſe men:</hi> ſo I ſeare me it may be to truly ſaid, there was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver leſſe piety in <hi>England,</hi> then in this long eontinuance of ſo many godly and zelous Paſtors. <hi>Sodome</hi> &amp; <hi>Gomer, Tire</hi> &amp; <hi>Sidon,</hi> ſhal riſe vp at the laſt day and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demn vs: for if halſe ſo many lecturs, and ſermons, &amp; exhortations, &amp; inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, had bin preached among them, as haue bin amonſt vs, <hi>They had ſurely repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted in ſackcloth &amp; aſhes. The Queene of the South,</hi> ſhall riſe vp in iudgment, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:4884:53"/>vs at the laſt day <hi>for ſhe came fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the vttermoſt part of the earth to heare the wiſdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e of Salomo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> Mat. 12.42. But ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny of vs, refuſe to ſtep out of our dores, to heare the heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly wiſdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e of the true <hi>Salomo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> Chriſt Ieſus, revealed in his hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly word. The <hi>Publicans and ſouldiers,</hi> ſhal riſe vp at the laſt day &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demn vs: for at the preaching of on <hi>Iohn Baptiſt, they were moued in their minds</hi> Luk. 3.14 But let al the Miniſters &amp; meſſengers of God, cry out til they be hoarce againſt our ſins, &amp; yet our harts ar nothing pric<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ked, &amp; yet our affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s are nothing ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vp. Thoſe wicked <hi>Iewes,</hi> that crucifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Lord of life, ſhal riſe vp at the laſt day &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demn vs; for they, at on ſermo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Peter,</hi> were co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>verted to the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber <hi>of three thouſand.</hi> Act. 2.41. But how many fermous ſhal a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> make a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt vs, before he convert on ſinfull ſoule, before hee bring home one ſtray ſheep to the ſheepfold of Chriſt Ieſus? The <hi>Ninivits</hi> as you haue hard, at one little ſermo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of a few words, delivered by
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:4884:53"/>one <hi>Ionas,</hi> repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted in ſackcloth &amp; aſhes, <hi>from the greateſt to the leaſt,</hi> but wee haue hard, not in this place only, but in al the corners, &amp; quarters of our la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dred <hi>Ionaſſes,</hi> yea many thouſand paſtors &amp; prophets, &amp; preachers of the word: &amp; yet for al this, where is our faith <hi>in beleeving God?</hi> wher are the <hi>faſts</hi> we haue <hi>proclaimed?</hi> wher is the <hi>ſackcloth we haue put on?</hi> wher are the ſuperiors to deſigne? where ar the inferiors to put in practiſe theſe holy exerciſes? Laſtly al the creaturs of God, ſhal riſe vp at the laſt day &amp; conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne vs: for they, in their ſeveral places, do in their kind, perform their duty to their creator, &amp; are obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to his word: but we only, as the moſt vnreaſonable, &amp; inſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſible of al other, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue obſtinat &amp; rebellious ſtil. The hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s declare the glory of God, the lights o<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bey him with fear, the ſtars ſhin in their watch, the moone keeps her appointed ſeaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> knows his going down, the waters fly at hi rebuke: the earth trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleth &amp; the mou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tains ſhak. The ſtork in
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:4884:54"/>the aier knoweth her appointed time, &amp; the turtle, and the crane, and the ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe obſerue the time of their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming: the oxe knoweth his owner, and the aſſe his maiſters cribb: but wee onely, as the moſt vnreaſonable, and inſenſible of al creatures continue obſtinate &amp; rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſtil. What ſhould I ſaie more (belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in Chriſt leſus) ſenſeleſſe ſtones are more obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to Gods voice the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we are. Beholde <hi>Moſes</hi> with his rod ſtroke the rocke but twice, <hi>and the vvaters guſhed out abundantly.</hi> Num. 20.11. but though the God of <hi>Moſes,</hi> ſtrik our ſtony hatts, twice twenty times, with the ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mer of his word: yet, where is that penitent <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> amongſt vs, J ſay not, that <hi>vveopeth bitterly,</hi> but that ſheddeth one teare, in remembrance of his tranſgreſſions? Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the ſtony wals of <hi>Iericho,</hi> after God had ſummoned them by his Prieſts, ſou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding their trumpets thrice, at the third found, <hi>fell flatte vpon the ground.</hi> Ioſ. 6.20. But we haue reſiſted, not the third, or the fourth, or the ſift onely, but more
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:4884:54"/>the fiue hundred ſolemne ſummons, &amp; ſeveral ſounds: none of them could ever moue vs, none of them coulde once a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wake vs. <hi>Iſidore in his</hi> 12. <hi>lib. and</hi> 2. <hi>cap. de brutis animalibus,</hi> reporteth of the yong Lions, that, after 3. daies, they are raiſed and rowſed, by the roaring of the olde: but the Lion of the tribe of <hi>Iudah</hi> Chriſt Ieſus, by preaching of his word, hath roared, not 3. daies alone but more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 43. yeares togither amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt vs, &amp; yet for al this we are not rouſed, and yet for al this we are not awaked. what? is not Chriſt the ſame Chriſt ſtill? is not his Goſpel as fruitful, is not his doctrine as effectual, is not his word as powerful now as ever it was? yes my deare bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren. But the fault is in vs. Our marble &amp; flinty harts will not be ſoftened, with the ſweete ſhewers of Gods heavenlie word, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fortably falling down vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: our ſtiffe &amp; yronſinewed necks, wil not bow with any yoke, either the <hi>ſweete &amp; eaſie</hi> voke of the Goſpel. Mat. 11.30. or the <hi>heavy &amp; vnſupportable</hi> yoke of the law.
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:4884:55"/>Act. 15.10. our faces are like whores for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heads, <hi>that wil not bluſh</hi> Ier. 3.3. our ears are ſo deafe, our eies ſo dry, our ſenſes ſo dul, our wils ſo obſtinat, our affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s ſo barren, our deſires ſo cold: that neither the infamy and ſhame of the world can moue vs, nor al ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tle admonitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s allure vs, nor the terrible threatnings of Gods iudgments feare vs, nor the continuall preaching of al the creatures of God vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der heave<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> perſwade vs vnto repentice. Nay we are ſo ſoundly rocked and lulled a ſleepe in the careleſſe cradell of ſecuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, that neither the goulden bells of <hi>Aa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron,</hi> nor the thundering trump of <hi>Eſay,</hi> nor the well tuned cymballs of <hi>Dauid,</hi> nor the ſhril ſou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of Gods word, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally ringing in our cares, ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> once awake vs. Being herein like to thoſe beares, of who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Selinus</hi> writeth, in his 39. <hi>chap. qui tam gravi ſemno premu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tur, vt ne vulne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribus quidem excitariqucant.</hi> who are ſo farre oppreſt with a heavy ſleepe, that though they bee wounded, yet can they not be wakened. Or like thoſe fiſhes of
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:4884:55"/>who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> in his 4. <abbr>l.</abbr> &amp; 10. c. <hi>de hiſt. animaliu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> writeth: <hi>that they ſleep ſo ſou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dly that, though they haue ſpeares thruſt into their ſides, yet they ſtir not at all:</hi> ſo ſenſe-leſſe alſo are we in this our carnal ſecuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, that though the Embaſſadours of the King of heave<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as ſo many ſons of thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, with <hi>Ionas</hi> in my text denou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce iudg<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment againſt vs, out of that word, which is ſharper the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> any two edged ſword: yet for al this, we do not with theſe <hi>Ninivits</hi> yeeld &amp; caſt down our ſelves before the Lord: but rather like to the dru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kard ſlee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping in the top of the maſt Pro 23. whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we are thus ſtrike<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we feel it not, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we are thus beaten we awake not, when we are thus admoniſhed we amend not.</p>
            <p>Wherfore (moſt deare &amp; bleſſed bre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> beloued in the bowels of Chriſt le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus) to conclud al in a word,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> as he ſaid to the Angel of the church that is at <hi>Sardis:</hi> ſo giue me leave, I beſeech yov, to ſay the ſame to every on of you, that hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth me this day. <hi>Reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber how you haue receaved &amp;c.</hi> Rev. 33. Reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber that this
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:4884:56"/>day you haue hard of a meſſage fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Lord to a great citty, &amp; of the converſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of a great citty vnto the Lord. Reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ber in the one Gods patie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to <hi>Niniveh,</hi> in ſparing it long <hi>Yet</hi> 40. <hi>daies:</hi> And yet his ſevere iudgme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of deſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, if ſhe would not amend, <hi>and Niniveh ſhalbe deſtroyed:</hi> Reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber in the other the <hi>Nini</hi> vits turning vnto the Lord, begun with <hi>faith,</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinued with <hi>faſting,</hi> declared in <hi>ſackcloth,</hi> performed of al, <hi>fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt vnto the leaſt.</hi> And reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber that the Lord hath ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, the ſame meſſag this day to <hi>England,</hi> to <hi>Lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>don,</hi> nay to vs all, as he did to <hi>Niniveh:</hi> giving vs yet time to re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pent, if we wil accept him. O then let vs loue him in his mercy: threatning our o verthrow, if we do neglect him, ô the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> let vs feare him in his iudgme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, let vs now repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, while we haue time, leaſt hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter we would repent, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we ſhal haue no time. Let vs now turn vnto the Lord, in <hi>beleeving on him,</hi> in pinching our bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies with <hi>faſting,</hi> in clothing our backes with <hi>ſackcloth,</hi> and in a general humilia<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:4884:56"/>of our ſelves before him, that ſo he may turne away his wrath, and heavie iudgmentes, from vs &amp; from our lande. Let vs now open our eares, at the ſou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of his word preached. That being ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, we may heare it carefully, &amp;, care<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fully hearing it, wee may conceiue it rightly, and, rightly conceiving it, wee may beleeue it faithfully, and, faithfully beleeving it, we may diſcerne it fruitful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and, fruitfully diſcerning it, we may practiſe it effectually, &amp; bring forth the fruits therof accordingly, therby <hi>grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from ſtrength to strength, from ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue to vertue, vntill at the laſt we become perfect men in Chriſt Ieſus.</hi> That ſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing nowe accepted as ſonnes, into the kingdome of <hi>grace</hi> in this world, wee may heerafter bee receaved as heires, into the kingdome of <hi>glory,</hi> in the world to come. Which the Lord of his infinit mercy graunt vnto vs all, for his Deare Sonns ſake Ieſus Chriſt, to whom with the Father, and the Holy Ghoſt, three Perſons, one eternall, everliving, and
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:4884:57"/>onely wiſe God, bee rendered and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cribed all Honour, and Glorie, Povver and Praiſe, Might and Maieſtie, Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie and Dominion, now and for ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FJNIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:4884:57"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
